<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/stylesheets/regional-xml-standalone.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE country-chap PUBLIC "-//IBFD//ELEMENTS COUNTRY-CHAP//EN" "http://dtd.ibfd.org/dtd/regionalbook.dtd">
<country-chap anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1" collection="wtj" doi="10.59403/d1ykhw" infotype="Journal_Article" pdf="wtj_2018_04_int_1.pdf">
   <chaphead anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_chaphead">
      <volume>10</volume>
      <number issuecomplete="y" pdf="wtj_2018_04.pdf">4</number>
      <month>November</month>
      <year>2019</year>
      <pubsection pscode="articles">Articles</pubsection><pubdate pubdate="2018-09-07">11 September 2018</pubdate>
      <title>What Is Really Wrong with Global Tax Governance and How to Properly Fix It</title>
      <country cc="o2"><countryname>OECD</countryname></country><country>
         <countryname>International</countryname>
      </country>
      <author anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_auth">
         <name firstname="T. Diniz" lastname="Magalhães">Tarcisio Diniz Magalhães<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_0" label="*">
               <p>
                  <emph type="b"> Postdoctoral Research Fellow, IBFD. PhD in Law and Justice, Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG). Visiting Researcher, </emph>
                  <emph type="bi">Université McGill </emph>
                  <emph type="b">(Stikeman Chair in Tax Law), </emph>
                  <emph type="bi">Wirtschaftsuniversität Wien</emph>
                  <emph type="b"> (WU) (</emph><emph type="bi">Institut für Österreichisches und Internationales Steuerrecht</emph><emph type="b">), and </emph>
                  <emph type="bi">Max-Planck-Gesellschaft </emph>
                  <emph type="b">(</emph><emph type="bi">Institut für Steuerrecht und Öffentliche Finanzen</emph><emph type="b">). Member of the Permanent Commission on Review and Simplification of Tax Legislation of the State of Minas Gerais, Brazil. This article builds on ideas first espoused in T. Magalhães, </emph>
                  <emph type="bi">International Taxation without International Representation? Legality and Legitimacy in Global Tax Governance</emph><emph type="b">, in</emph>
                  <emph type="bi"> Building Trust in Taxation</emph>
                  <emph type="b"> (B. Peeters, H. Gribnau &amp; J. Badisco eds., Intersentia 2017), and expanded into a PhD Thesis entitled “Critical Theory of International Tax Law”. For helpful support, discussions and suggestions during the development of my arguments, I would like to thank Professors Misabel Derzi, Pasquale Pistone, Onofre Batista Júnior, Allison Christians, Ludmila Oliveira, Wolfgang Schön, Hans Gribnau, Bruno Peeters, Dries Lesage, Joanna Wheeler, Luís Eduardo Schoueri, Ricardo Garcia Antón, Irma Mosquera Valderrama, Tsilly Dagan, Sérgio André Rocha, Fabrício Polido, Rafhael Frattari, Valter Lobato, Stephen Shay, Diane Ring, Peter Dietsch, Thomas Rixen, Cees Peters, as well as researchers at UFMG, McGill, WU and Max Planck, especially Fernanda Alen, Marcela Ribeiro, Marina Marinho, Nathalia Domingues, Thiago Feital, Priscilla César, Ricardo Rodrigues, Pedro Schoueri, Stjepan Gadzo, Andrzej Stasio, Jean-Philippe West, Sriram Govind, Andrés Moreno, Leopoldo Parada. Gratitude also goes to the anonymous peer reviewers and to the participants at the Institute for Global Law &amp; Policy (IGLP) 2018 Conference: “Law in Global Political Economy: Heterodoxy Now”, held at Harvard Law School. This project benefitted from research grants by </emph>
                  <emph type="bi">Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais </emph>
                  <emph type="b">(FAPEMIG). The author can be contacted at <url target="t.magalhaes@ibfd.org" type="mail">t.magalhaes@ibfd.org</url>. </emph>
               </p>
            </footnote>
         </name>
      </author>
      <summary>During the course of the last 100 years, the wealthiest and most powerful nations on the planet have systematically gathered around in small groups of experts, scientific committees and working parties, under the auspices of the League of Nations and the OECD, to decide on the appropriate tax policy norms for global implementation. The immediate consequence was, and still is, the creation of an exclusionary architecture that deprives the majority of the world’s countries from meaningfully influencing legal-institutional choices vis-à-vis what countries should tax cross-border transactions, a process that has clear global distributional implications. This article sets off to investigate this process of exclusion. It identifies two central elements that constrain broad participation in global tax governance, engendering the under-representation of the interests of developing countries: expertise and power. As further argued, the international tax arena is better understood as an entrenched political space, where influential actors maintain their privileged positions by dominating the debate and decision-making procedures. The author then proceeds to analyse possible remedies to  this cartelistic and bureaucratic club model of international taxation governance, such as the creation of new intergovernmental organizations or forums, concluding that all proposals so far end up reproducing the same top-down technocratic mentality embedded in the work of the League of Nations and the OECD. Rejecting old and new solutions for a just world tax order, what the author believes is actually needed is a completely different approach, grounded on contested multilateral practices and diversity of world views. Using critical legal theory, the goal is to provide an alternative way to think (politically) about fiscal relations among developed and developing states.</summary>
   </chaphead>
   <chapbody>
      
      <longquote><p><emph type="i">“Who decides what and how to tax, and for whose benefit?”</emph><footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_1" label="1."><p>P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen, <emph type="i">Global Tax Governance: What It Is and Why It Matters</emph>, in <emph type="i">Global Tax Governance: What Is Wrong with It and How to Fix It</emph> p. 8 (P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen eds., ECPR 2016).</p></footnote></p></longquote><section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_1" label="1.">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Time and time again, the richest and most powerful nations on the planet gather around to decide the fate of global economic and fiscal policymaking.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_2" label="2.">
               <p> D. Held, <emph type="i">Cosmopolitanism: Ideals and Realities</emph> pp. 1-2 (Polity 2010):</p>
               <longquote>
                  <p>Until recently, the West has, by and large, determined the rules of the game on the global stage. During the last century, Western countries presided over a shift in world power – from control via territory to control via the creation of governance structures created in the post-1945 era. From the United Nations Charter and the formation of the Bretton-Woods institutions to the Rio Declaration on the environment and the creation of the World Trade Organization, international agreements have invariably served to entrench a well-established international power structure. The division of the globe into powerful nation-states, with distinctive sets of geopolitical interests, and reflecting the international power structure of 1945, is still embedded in the articles and statutes of leading intergovernmental organizations, such as the IMF and the World Bank. Voting rights are distributed largely in relation to individual financial contributions, and geo-economic strength is integrated into decision-making procedures. The result has been susceptibility of the major international governmental organizations (IGOs) to the agendas of the most powerful states, partiality in enforcement operations (or lack of them altogether), their continued dependency on financial support from a few major states, and weaknesses in the policing of global collective action problems. This has been dominance based on a “club” model of global governance and legitimacy. Policy at the international level has been decided by a core set of powerful countries, above all the “G1”, G5 and G7, with the rest largely excluded from the decision-making process.</p>
               </longquote>
            </footnote> As it often happens in international tax law, a small number of rich countries dominate the field, imposing their wills globally through non-binding mechanisms, sometimes referred to as soft power and soft law.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_3" label="3.">
               <p> 
                  <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., P. Essers, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2014_02_int_2">International Tax Justice between Machiavelli and Habermas</extxref></emph>, 68 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 42 (2014), Journals IBFD, republished in<emph type="i"> Building Trust in Taxation</emph> (B. Peeters, H. Gribnau &amp; J. Badisco eds., Intersentia 2017); C. Peters, <emph type="i"><extxref target="olit_head">On the Legitimacy of International Tax Law</extxref></emph> (IBFD 2014), Online Books IBFD; I.J.M. Valderrama, <emph type="i"><extxref target="wtj_2015_03_int_3">Legitimacy and the Making of International Tax Law: The Challenges of Multilateralism</extxref></emph>, 7 World Tax J. 3 (2015), Journals IBFD; I. Burges &amp; I. Mosquera, <emph type="i">Corporate Taxation and BEPS: A Fair Slice for Developing Countries</emph>, 1 ELR 29 (2017); I.J.M. Valderrama, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2018_03_int_2">Output Legitimacy Deficits and the Inclusive Framework of the OECD/G20 Base Erosion and Profit Shifting Initiative</extxref></emph>, 72 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 3 (2018), Journals IBFD; R.G. Antón, <emph type="i"><extxref target="wtj_2016_02_int_3">The 21st Century Multilateralism in International Taxation: The Emperor’s New Clothes?</extxref></emph>, 8 World Tax J. 2 (2016), Journals IBFD; S.A. Rocha, <emph type="i">The Other Side of BEPS: “Imperial Taxation” and the “International Tax Imperialism”</emph>, in <emph type="i">Tax Sovereignty in the BEPS Era</emph> (S.A. Rocha &amp; A. Christians eds., Wolters Kluwer 2017); R.J.S. Tavares, <emph type="i">Country-by-Country Reporting? National Sovereignty, International Tax Transparency, and the Inclusive Framework on BEPS</emph>, in <emph type="i">Tax Sovereignty in the BEPS Era</emph> (S.A. Rocha &amp; A. Christians eds., Wolters Kluwer 2017); A. Christians &amp; S. Shay, <emph type="i">Assessing BEPS: Origins, Standards, and Responses </emph>(IFA Cahiers vol. 102A, 2017), Online Books IBFD; A. Christians &amp; L. van Apeldoorn, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2018_04_o2_1">The OECD Inclusive Framework</extxref></emph>, 72 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 4/5 (2018), Journals IBFD. </p>
            </footnote> Recently, confronted with tremendous public criticism of the flawed outcomes of their own past policy choices, the same affluent nations now claim that they are capable of, and committed to, meaningful change. Their latest initiative, and arguably one of the most comprehensive and resolute of all, the well-known and much discussed BEPS Action Plan,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_4" label="4.">
               <p> 
                  <emph type="i">See </emph>OECD, <emph type="i"><extxref target="oecd_tt_report_addressing_base_erosion_2013">Addressing Base Erosion and Profit Shifting</extxref> </emph>(OECD 2013), International Organizations’ Documentation IBFD; OECD, <emph type="i"><extxref target="oecd_tt_report_beps_action_plan_2013">Action Plan on Base Erosion and Profit Shifting</extxref></emph> (OECD 2013), International Organizations’ Documentation IBFD. But<emph type="i"> see </emph>OXFAM, <emph type="i">Business Among Friends: Why Corporate Tax Dodgers Are Not Yet Losing Sleep Over Global Tax Reform</emph>, OXFAM Briefing Paper 182 (OXFAM 2014); Y. Brauner, <emph type="i">Transfer Pricing in BEPS: First Round – Business Interests Win (But, Not in Knock-Out)</emph>, 43 Intertax 1 (2015). For scholarly assessments of each of the 15 proposed actions, <emph type="i">see</emph> Y. Brauner, <emph type="i">What the BEPS?</emph>, 16 Fla. Tax Rev. 2 (2014); Y. Brauner, <emph type="i">Treaties in the Aftermath of BEPS</emph>, 41 Brook. J. Intl. L. 3 (2016); R.S. Avi-Yonah &amp; H.Xu, <emph type="i">Evaluating BEPS: A Reconsideration of the Benefits Principle and Proposal for UN Oversight</emph>, 6 Harv. Bus. L. Rev. 2 (2016), short version: R.S. Avi-Yonah &amp; H.Xu, <emph type="i">Evaluating BEPS</emph>, in <emph type="i">Tax Sovereignty in the BEPS Era</emph> (S.A. Rocha &amp; A. Christians eds., Wolters Kluwer 2017); A. Christians, <emph type="i">BEPS and the New International Tax Order</emph>, 2016 BYU L. Rev. (2017). </p>
            </footnote> consists of a coordinated global tax reform attempt by the Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development (OECD), a 35-member group of mostly industrialized countries. The announced objective is to stop a global base erosion and profit shifting epidemic, which, however, stems from the very international tax regime (ITR) those countries themselves set up a century ago, and which they made sure would remain as close as possible to its original intent. </p>
         <p>As its starting point, this article takes the basic assumption that commitments to substantively changing policies will never be enough without concern for the process itself. As a precondition for the success of any long-term regime, and with regard to the legitimacy of its substantive rules, changes of an inclusive nature need to be made to the institutional background in which policy deliberations are carried out. The main challenge facing international tax governance is not what norms or standards should be implemented across the globe, but the absence of proper venues for all countries, especially developing ones, to fully participate in and influence the process of policymaking.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_5" label="5.">
               <p> As such, this article is a (different) response to the double question contained in the subtitle of a recently published compilation of papers: P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen eds., <emph type="i">Global Tax Governance: What Is Wrong with It and How to Fix It</emph> (ECPR 2016).</p>
            </footnote> In this age of postnational legal order,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_6" label="6.">
               <p> For the concept of postnational law, <emph type="i">see </emph>N. Krisch, <emph type="i">The Case for Pluralism in Postnational Law</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Worlds of European Constitutionalism</emph> (G. de Búrca &amp; J.H.H. Weiler eds., Cambridge University 2012); N. Krisch, <emph type="i">Pouvoir Constituant and Pouvoir Irritant in the Postnational Order</emph>, 14 Intl. J. Const. L. 3 (2016).</p>
            </footnote> participatory legitimacy and accountability must be the defining characteristics of any supranational institution or regime set up to address international taxation issues, embodying the old adage that for so long served to legitimize national tax states: “no taxation without representation”.</p>
         <p>Thus, the aim of this article is to offer democratic alternatives to address global fiscal challenges, such as tax competition, base erosion and the global distribution of tax revenues. It starts by showing how and why global tax governance has always evolved through technocratic discourses that were conducted by unaccountable international organizations (IOs) under the control of powerful players. The argument is that what is missing in most analysis is a more radical perspective that takes struggles in the international tax arena seriously,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_7" label="7.">
               <p> On the problematic of power, <emph type="i">see </emph>K. Nielsen, <emph type="i">Globalization and Justice</emph> p. 282 (Humanity Books 2003): “We need ... to be concerned about attaining or approximating equality in relations of power. We need, in being concerned with that, to be concerned with the kinds of social structures, including modes of production, that place some in positions of dominance and control and place others in positions of submission and powerlessness. We need to see how this works both domestically and internationally. What is crucial to look at is the forms of social organization that produce and sustain relations of power and exploitation”; R. Geuss, <emph type="i">Philosophy and Real Politics</emph> p. 94 (Princeton University 2008): “A theoretical approach with no place for a theory of power is not merely deeply deficient but actively pernicious, because mystifying”; R. Forst, <emph type="i">The Right to Justification: Elements of a Constructivist Theory of Justice</emph> p. 258 (J. Flynn trans., Columbia University 2012): “One can say ... that the question of power is <emph type="i">the first question of justice</emph>. This stresses the need for a theory that focuses not just on justice in the distribution of goods, but on the justice of the ‘basic structure’ of relations of political and economic power, that is, relations of government, of production, and of distribution”.</p>
            </footnote> as well as the presence of radical pluralism on the global stage.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_8" label="8.">
               <p><emph type="i"> See</emph>, e.g., N. Krisch, <emph type="i">Who is Afraid of Radical Pluralism? Legal Order and Political Stability in the Postnational Space</emph>, 24 <emph type="i">Ratio Juris </emph>4 (2011), claiming that the legal philosopher Neil MacCormick should not have abandoned his radical pluralist ideas, in favour of an institutional pluralism. </p>
            </footnote> To that end, it is necessary to engage with the tradition of critical legal theory, as applied to international law and relations.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_9" label="9.">
               <p> Among jurists, Critical Legal Studies (CLS) was an important movement in the United States starting in the 1970s, which also migrated to the field of international law, especially through the work of David Kennedy and Martti Koskenniemi, together with the so-called Third-World Approaches to International Law (TWAIL), the New Approaches to International Law (NAIL), and so on. For the CLS movement, <emph type="i">see</emph> R.M. Unger, <emph type="i">The Critical Legal Studies Movement: Another Time, a Greater Task</emph> (2nd ed., Verso 2015). On the many different possible critical approaches to international law, <emph type="i">see </emph>P. Singh &amp; B. Mayer eds., <emph type="i">Critical International Law: Postrealism, Postcolonialism, and Transnationalism</emph> (Oxford University 2014); A. Bianchi, <emph type="i">International Law Theories: An Inquiry into Different Ways of Thinking</emph> (Oxford University 2016).</p>
            </footnote> From such a theoretical framework, this article goes on to critically evaluate a set of alternatives to our “club model”<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_10" label="10.">
               <p> R.O. Keohane &amp; J.S. Nye Jr., <emph type="i">The Club Model of Multilateral Cooperation and Problems of Democratic Legitimacy</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Power and Governance in a Partially Globalized World</emph> (R.O. Keohane ed., Routledge 2002), describing the democratic deficit of the club model and suggesting steps to improve the legitimacy of international institutions.</p>
            </footnote> of global tax governance. These include the creation of a separate, stand-alone “International (World) Tax Organization”, and the establishment of informal “tax cooperation forums” (TCFs), as proposed by policy experts in the past and by philosophers, political scientists and tax scholars in more recent years. However, the conclusion is that none of these proposals provides an adequate response to the identified problems of expertise and power. The importance of both attention and fidelity to fundamental democratic values by countries and institutions that wield (and jealously guard) an outsized influence on international taxation today should not be underestimated. Nonetheless, the author submits that for a legitimate world tax order to become a reality it is pressing to incorporate the ideas of multipolarity and pluralism.</p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_2" label="2.">
         <title>International Taxation without International Representation: How Our “Unruly World of Tax” Is Part of the Same Old “World of Struggle”</title>
         <p>In his most recent book, “A World of Struggle: How Power, Law, and Expertise Shape Global Political Economy”, David Kennedy sheds new light on how the international institutional and legal order that exists conforms to the manoeuvres of technocrats, in competition with the classical figures of powerful states and global capital. As Kennedy explains, these actors, through their never-ending linguistic and knowledge battles over how to “improve” the structure of the global economy, promote (intentionally or otherwise) a certain division and allocation of power, wealth, status and opportunity among nations: </p>
         <longquote>
            <p>In a world where so much is open to debate and conflict is all around us, how can it be so difficult to contest and change the things that matter? Things like the distribution of wealth and opportunity or honor and shame. Or the pattern of environmental destruction. Or the ubiquity of kleptocratic rule. The answer is not a mysterious constitutional settlement, the obscure workings of a disaggregated public hand or global value consensus. The answer lies in the strange alchemy of expertise and struggle through which our world is made and remade. [...] In our world, indeterminate language and uncertain knowledge distribute wealth and power. That is strange – and hard to render visible, let alone contest.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_11" label="11.">
                  <p> D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">A World of Struggle: How Power, Law, and Expertise Shape Global Political Economy</emph> pp. 1-2 (Princeton University 2016).</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
         </longquote>
         <p>Although Kennedy’s in-depth analysis does not deal with international tax law, the story his book tells and the picture of law and globalization it paints make even more sense after examining how the ITR was created, how it progressed over the years and is still being shaped today. </p>
         <p>This is one of the gaps this article tries to fill: to reveal the alchemy of expertise and power through which international tax law is made and remade. This effort is worthwhile considering that tax scholars have tended to overlook questions of power and the existence of asymmetric and dependency relationships among diverse tax states. One clear example is a recent paper – discussed in <xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_2_2">section 3.2.2.</xref> – that calls our world of tax “unruly”, paving the way for the authors’ proposal on how to turn such a world into a well-ordered one.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_12" label="12.">
               <p> 
                  <emph type="i">See </emph>H.D. Rosenbloom, N. Noked &amp; M.S. Helal, <emph type="i">The Unruly World of Tax: A Proposal for an International Tax Cooperation Forum</emph>, 15 Fla. Tax Rev. 2 (2014).</p>
            </footnote> Challenging such a view, this article claims and demonstrates that our tax order is hegemonic and distributionally biased, being governed by a few players. </p>
         <p>Therefore, it is better to avoid describing the ITR as if it were a system free of domination and exclusion mechanisms, and focus on confronting the problem of <emph type="i">misrepresentation</emph> in the international tax arena – which critical theorist Nancy Fraser considers being “the defining issue of <emph type="i">the political</emph>” [emphasis added].<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13" label="13.">
               <p> N. Fraser, <emph type="i">Scales of Justice: Reimagining Political Space in a Globalizing World</emph> p. 18 (Columbia University 2009); N. Fraser, <emph type="i">Fortunes of Feminism: From State-Managed Capitalism to Neoliberal Crisis</emph> 196 (2013). Classically, <emph type="i">the political</emph> was conceptualized by the legal theorist Carl Schmitt as the friend-enemy distinction – which is particularly useful to describe the OECD’s fight against tax havens or multinationals, as responsible for tax evasion, avoidance and base erosion. <emph type="i">See </emph>C. Schmitt, <emph type="i">The Concept of the Political</emph> (2nd ed., G. Schwab ed., 2007).</p>
            </footnote> When it comes to international taxation, developing countries have been continuously alienated on the basis that they lack the appropriate technical knowledge. But even when such countries possess some expertise, power politics carries the day. This is confirmed by the absence of experts from non-OECD member countries actively participating in decision-making processes on global tax regulation and management. </p>
         <p>These two factors – expertise and power, as shapers of international tax law – have a tendency to coexist, so much so that it is impossible to understand one without the other. Being intrinsically interwoven makes it hard to distinguish them in practice.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_14" label="14.">
               <p> For some, along the same lines of Michel Foucault’s and Pierre Bourdieu’s philosophical critiques, knowledge and politics can never be completely separated, because one is constitutive of the other. <emph type="i">See </emph>S. Picciotto, <emph type="i">Indeterminacy, Complexity, Technocracy and the Reform of International Corporate Taxation</emph>, 24 Social &amp; Legal Studies 2 (2015), applying a Bourdieusian perspective; M. Kilanowski, <emph type="i">The Questionable Role of Experts in Global Governance: Beyond David Kennedy Approach</emph>, 15 Ekonomia i Prawo. Econ. &amp; Law 4 (2016), applying a Foucaultian perspective.</p>
            </footnote> For methodological reasons, however, this article will approach each of them separately.</p>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_2_1" label="2.1.">
            <title>Expertise as a source of misrepresentation, or the problem of technocracy</title>
            <p>Despite its undeniable relevance in modern societies, expert knowledge can pose real obstacles to democratic legitimation of policy decisions through public debate and scrutiny.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_15" label="15.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See generally </emph>L.C. Bresser-Pereira, <emph type="i">Technobureaucratic Capitalism</emph> (1990) [English translation of a published book in Portuguese], available at <url target="http://www.bresserpereira.org.br/BOOKS/1990TechnobureaucraticCapitalism.i.pdf">http://www.bresserpereira.org.br/BOOKS/1990TechnobureaucraticCapitalism.i.pdf</url>; F. Fischer, <emph type="i">Democracy and Expertise: Reorienting Public Inquiry</emph> (Oxford University 2009); M.B. Brown, <emph type="i">Science in Democracy: Expertise, Institutions, and Representation</emph> (The MIT 2009); E. Dargent, <emph type="i">Technocracy and Democracy in Latin America: The Experts Running Government </emph>(Cambridge University 2015); J. Habermas, <emph type="i">The Lure of Technocracy </emph>(C. Cronin trans., Polity 2015); P.M. Wood, <emph type="i">Technocracy Rising: The Trojan Horse of Global Transformation</emph> (Coherent 2015); O.J. Sending, <emph type="i">The Politics of Expertise: Competing for Authority in Global Governance</emph> (University of Michigan 2015); D.M. Levy &amp; S.J. Peart, <emph type="i">Escape from Democracy: The Role of Experts and the Public in Economic Policy</emph> (Cambridge University 2017). For an international tax law perspective, <emph type="i">see </emph>Picciotto, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_14">n. 14</xref>.</p>
               </footnote> From the outset, technical discourses in general have the propensity to hide, behind a veil of neutrality and scientificity, normative assumptions about what is right and wrong, what is fair and unfair, while denying the presence of ideologies and entrenched power relations.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_16" label="16.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph> J. Habermas, <emph type="i">Toward a Rational Society: Student Protest, Science, and Politics </emph>p. 111 (J.J. Shapiro trans., Polity 1970): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>Technocratic consciousness is, on the one hand, “less ideological” than all previous ideologies. For it does not have the opaque force of a delusion that only transfigures the implementation of interests. On the other hand today’s dominant, rather glassy background ideology, which makes a fetish of science, is more irresistible and farther-reaching than ideologies of the old type. For with the veiling of practical problems it not only justifies a <emph type="i">particular class’s </emph>interest in domination and represses <emph type="i">another class’s </emph>partial need for emancipation, but affects the human race’s emancipatory interest as such.</p>
                  </longquote>
               </footnote> This is especially true in the case of tax law.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_17" label="17.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph> L. Philipps, <emph type="i">Discursive Deficits: A Feminist Perspective on the Power of Technical Knowledge in Fiscal Law and Policy</emph>, 11 CJLS/RCDS 1 (1996), short version in<emph type="i"> Critical Tax Theory: An Introduction</emph> (A.C. Infanti &amp; B.J. Crawford eds., Cambridge University 2009), exposing the ways in which technical discourses in the area of fiscal law and policy can be constructed as purely scientific and morally neutral, thus rationalizing social inequalities by making them look “normal”. </p>
               </footnote> Expertise also shields political discussions and delegitimizes moral disagreements, excluding from participation and observation those who are deemed non-specialists, even when they will be affected by the outcomes of the policies. Although the fact that tax law is inherently political in nature has never really escaped tax scholars,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_18" label="18.">
                  <p> A.C. Infanti &amp; B.J. Crawford, <emph type="i">Introduction</emph>, in <emph type="i">Critical Tax Theory: An Introduction</emph> p.xxi (A.C. Infanti &amp; B.J. Crawford eds., Cambridge University 2009): “Tax law is political”.</p>
               </footnote> they have not always been able to maintain a politically critical view in the face of the technicality of their field.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_19" label="19.">
                  <p> M.A. Livingston, <emph type="i">Radical Scholars, Conservative Field: Putting “Critical Tax Scholarship” in Perspective</emph>, 76 N.C. L. Rev. p. 1791 (1998).</p>
               </footnote> As a result, international tax scholarship – like its national counterpart<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_20" label="20.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., M.A. Livingston, <emph type="i">Reinventing Tax Scholarship: Lawyers, Economists, and the Role of the Legal Academy</emph>, 83 Cornell L. Rev. 2 (1998), evaluating the state of tax scholarship and making the recommendations that academic lawyers reinvent their field by expanding their methods to include more than economic studies, in dialogue with psychology, political and social sciences; A. Christians et al., <emph type="i">Taxation as a Global Socio-Legal Phenomenon</emph>, 14 ILSA J. Intl. &amp; Comp. L. 2, p. 303 (2008): “tax scholarship should turn to fields such as international relations, organizational theory, and political philosophy to provide a broader framework for understanding the rapid changes that are taking place in tax policy and politics in the United States and around the world”; D. Ring, <emph type="i">The Promise of International Tax Scholarship and Its Implications for Research Design, Theory, and Methodology</emph>, 55 St. Louis U. L. J. 307 (2010), proposing that international tax legal scholars expand their methodologies and research agendas, engaging with other fields, like international relations theory.</p>
               </footnote> – has been dominated by a “culture of apolitical expert rule”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_21" label="21.">
                  <p> The expression comes from Martti Koskenniemi, a critical international legal scholar whose work has sought to bring to the fore how the mainstream managerial approach to international law tends to downplay “the role of will and randomness, passion and ideology in the way the world is governed, and their own implication in it”. M. Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">The Politics of International Law </emph>pp. 73-74 (Hart 2011).</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>The political dimension of (tax) law turns out to be even more apparent in the international realm, as international law navigates “between politics and technique”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_22" label="22.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 331. <emph type="i">See also</emph> Kennedy’s pieces, especially D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">The Politics of the Invisible College: International Governance and the Politics of Expertise</emph>, 5 E.H.R.L.R. (2001); D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">Challenging Expert Rule: The Politics of Global Governance</emph>, 27 Sydney L. Rev. 5 (2005); Kennedy, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_11">n. 11</xref>, at pp. 1-2.</p>
               </footnote> Typically, those who try to cultivate a way of thinking of international law “in apolitical and technical terms” pay the high cost of allowing “expert rule and managerialism, not in competition with politics as in the domestic realm, but as a <emph type="i">substitute </emph>for it”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_23" label="23.">
                  <p> Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_21">n. 21</xref>, at p. 359.</p>
               </footnote> This managerial approach, with its emphasis on informal regimes, transgovernmental networks and soft institutions, pervades international tax reasoning,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_24" label="24.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>A. Christians, <emph type="i">Networks, Norms, and National Tax Policy</emph>, 9 Wash. U. Global Stud. L. Rev. 1 (2010).</p>
               </footnote> where soft law is extensively used and abused.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_25" label="25.">
                  <p> D. Ring, <emph type="i">Who is Making International Tax Policy? International Organizations as Power Players in a High Stakes World</emph>, 33 Fordham Intl. L. J. 649, p. 652 (2010): “despite the formal, hard law power of the state over international tax policy, international organizations influence the actual design of international tax policy and tax rules in a variety of ways, up to and including the creation or exercise of ‘soft law’ power”; S.A. Dean, <emph type="i">Neither Rules nor Standards</emph>, 87 Notre Dame L. Rev. 2, p. 554 (2011): “Rather than a contest between rules and standards, the dynamics of the international tax regime tend to be viewed in terms of hard and soft law”. For a discussion of the implications of adhering to the soft law grammar in the context of international tax policy, <emph type="i">see</emph> A. Christians, <emph type="i">Hard Law, Soft Law, and International Taxation</emph>, 25 Wis. Intl. L. J. 2, p. 332 (2007), claiming that “[i]f the OECD is described as a source of soft law, nations may be expected to comply with its guidance even if they are not legally obligated to do so”.</p>
               </footnote> The drawback is that seeing law as a managerial technique results in depoliticizing the ITR,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_26" label="26.">
                  <p> For a similar line of thought, <emph type="i">see </emph>M. Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">From Apology to Utopia: The Structure of International Legal Argument</emph> (Cambridge University 2005); Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_21">n. 21</xref>, at p. 35 et seq.</p>
               </footnote> in turn obscuring underlying imperial relations and patterns of domination. No attention is paid to the exercise of political and economic power by a few players who can shape the rules of the game to their own benefit.</p>
            <p>For instance, Reuven Avi-Yonah has relentlessly argued, against Michael Graetz, H. David Rosenbloom, Tsilly Dagan, Julie Roin, Mitchell Kane, Daniel Shaviro and others, that the primary principles of the ITR are so universally accepted that they ought to be viewed as part of customary international law.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_27" label="27.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">International Tax as International Law: An Analysis of the International Tax Regime</emph> (Cambridge University 2007). <emph type="i">Accord </emph>Y. Brauner, <emph type="i">An International Tax Regime in Crystallization</emph>, 56 Tax L. Rev. (2003), republished in <emph type="i">International Tax Law</emph>, vol. 1 (R.S. Avi-Yonah ed., Edward Elgar 2016).</p>
               </footnote> The most significant implication of endorsing such a controversial view is that once the ITR is presented as a “coherent” set of “neutral”<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_28" label="28.">
                  <p> The author thanks Tsilly Dagan for reminding him that one major flaw in this description consists in the fact that coherence does not necessarily imply neutrality. As an example, she mentions networks that, although built around a compatible standard, can still be used to serve and benefit its owners/initiators.</p>
               </footnote> principles for defining and dividing the global tax base, countries are said to be constrained in choosing otherwise.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_29" label="29.">
                  <p> R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">Comment</emph>, 53 Tax L. Rev. pp. 169-170 (2000): “I would argue that the freedom of most countries to adopt international tax rules is severely constrained, even before entering into any tax treaties, by the need to adapt to generally accepted principles of international taxation”.</p>
               </footnote> Going even further, another tax scholar, Eduardo Baistrocchi, has recently advanced the idea that the ITR is nothing more than a “legal technology designed by the League of Nations in the 1920s” and “encapsulated in the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development Model Tax Convention on Income and on Capital (OECD Model)”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_30" label="30.">
                  <p> E.A. Baistrocchi, <emph type="i">The International Tax Regime and the BRIC World: Elements for a Theory</emph>, 33 Oxford J. Legal Stud. 4, p. 734 (2013).</p>
               </footnote> Particularly, Baistrocchi portrays the process of tax norm emulation concerning transfer pricing rules among the emerging economies of BRICs (Brazil, Russia, India and China) as part of an evolutionary and linear path to global convergence towards technical progress.</p>
            <p>These views implicitly suggest that countries that are considered underdeveloped need to catch up with developed ones by constructing tax systems that are similar to the dominant model.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_31" label="31.">
                  <p> This has been the prevailing rationale behind expert-led tax reforms in developing countries for decades and decades. Compare N. Kaldor, <emph type="i">Will Underdeveloped Countries Learn to Tax?</emph>, Foreign Aff. (1963), with P. Genschel &amp; L. Seelkopf, <emph type="i">Did They Learn to Tax? Taxation Trends Outside the OECD</emph>, 23 Rev. Int’l Pol. Econ. 2, pp. 317 and 340 (2016): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>The question Kaldor really meant to ask was whether underdeveloped countries could learn to tax like advanced Western democracies. He seemed to take more or less for granted that the rich Western democracies of the OECD-area embodied the hopes and ambitions of the developing rest of the world (RoW). In order to catch up with the West economically and socially, developing countries had to adopt Western methods of taxation, so Kaldor reasoned. [...] For Nicholas Kaldor it went without saying that Western tax systems were the role model for the RoW. International organizations model much of their tax policy advice on Western experience partly because they are often still dominated by Western countries and partly because the West is still the largest reservoir of tax policy expertise. And also academics tend to take the tax policies of OECD countries as their point of departure simply because most data are available on it. </p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>For a discussion of tax expertise, <emph type="i">see </emph>M. Stewart, <emph type="i">“Waiting for Consensus of the Experts?” Expert Discourse and the Politics of Tax Reform</emph>, Working Paper (University of Melbourne 2005), available at 
                     <url target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1532645">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1532645</url>; A.J. Cockfield, <emph type="i">Purism and Contextualism within International Tax Law Analysis: How Traditional Analysis Fails Developing Countries</emph>, 5 eJournal Tax Res. 2 (2007).</p>
               </footnote> These are just a few examples of how experts – <emph type="i">in casu</emph>, jurists, but the category includes professional lawyers, accountants, economists and even philosophers<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32" label="32.">
                  <p> Philosophers, like the ones discussed below – <emph type="i">see </emph>P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen, <emph type="i">Tax Competition and Global Background Justice</emph>, 22 J. Pol. Phil. 2 (2014); P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen, <emph type="i">Redistribution, Globalisation, and Multi-Level Governance</emph>, 1 Moral Phil. &amp; Polit. 1 (2014); D. Bamford, <emph type="i">Realising International Justice: To Constrain or to Counter-Incentivise?</emph>, 1 Moral Phil. &amp; Pol. 1 (2014) – behave as experts when they put disagreement and political deliberation aside and perform the monological role of enlightened philosopher kings, offering “her (or, more usually, his) own view of what justice consists in, what rights we have, what fair terms of social co-operation would be, and what all of this is based on”. J. Waldron, <emph type="i">Law and Disagreement</emph> p. 1 (Clarendon 1999). <emph type="i">See also </emph>H. Kelsen, <emph type="i">Platonic Justice</emph>, in <emph type="i">What is Justice? Justice, Law, and Politics in the Mirror of Science: Collected Essays by Hans Kelsen</emph> (Lawbook Exchange 2013): “Since the ruling philosopher has a knowledge of the divine good and is unique in the possession of his secret, he is entirely different from other men. The mass of people, who have no political rights, have no choice but to believe in the wisdom and grace of the ruler”; R. Forst, <emph type="i">Justification and Critique: Towards a Critical Theory of Politics</emph> pp. 1 and 4 (Ciaran Cronin trans., 2014): “All too often political philosophy continues to live in a pre-democratic era. It accords priority to teleological values which are supposed to ground a just or good social order, where those who are subjected to this order do not feature in it as authors”; R. Rorty, <emph type="i">The Priority of Democracy to Philosophy</emph>, in <emph type="i">Philosophical Papers vol. 1: Objectivity, Relativism, and Truth</emph> (Cambridge University 1991), decrying Enlightenment philosophers who believe in the possibility of providing rationalistic and ahistorical justifications for “moral truths” and “right answers”. In the international tax context, Steven Dean uses the Platonic figure of the philosopher king in a somewhat different manner, emphasizing the illusion of economically rational sovereigns that always act in order to maximize national welfare. S.A. Dean, <emph type="i">Philosopher Kings and International Tax: A New Approach to Tax Havens, Tax Flight, and International Tax Cooperation</emph>, 58 Hastings L. J. 911, p. 965 (2007), commending the abandonment of the philosopher king model in international tax for an integrated theory, as the one developed by Oona Hathaway, which “acknowledges and attempts to make sense of the array of political and economic pressures that drive a nation’s decision-making process”.</p>
               </footnote> – can contribute to the enforcement of a specific set of ideas, as if such ideas were neutral and regardless of their distributional implications. Yet these ideas are not politically, economically or socially neutral, nor are they uncontroversial.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_33" label="33.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>J.E. Stiglitz, <emph type="i">The Euro: How a Common Currency Threatens the Future of Europe</emph> (W.W. Norton &amp; Company 2016): “certain ideas do serve certain interests, and we should not be surprised that by and large tend to serve the interests of those who make them, even if they use the more abstract ideas to argue for them. This analysis leads to an inevitable conclusion: economics and politics cannot be separated – as much as economists would like them to be”.</p>
               </footnote> Instead, they are responsible for how resources are allocated across time and place. It makes a difference whose ideas become dominant and therefore deserving of emulation by others. As Kennedy puts it, “to say the world is covered in law is also to say we are increasingly governed by experts” who “make decisions that affect the wealth, status and power of other people”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_34" label="34.">
                  <p> Kennedy, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_22">n. 22</xref>, at p. 6. </p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, even if these authors were correct in their description of the ITR, it cannot be assumed that convergence is necessarily a good thing. Such an uncritical narrative contributes to the maintenance of an unjust status quo.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_35" label="35.">
                  <p> As the work of Carole Pateman demonstrates, under circumstances of structural domination and subordination, as well as massive inequalities, it is an illusion to talk about meaningful consent. <emph type="i">See generally </emph>D.I. O’Neill, M.L. Shanley &amp; I.M. Young eds., <emph type="i">Illusion of Consent: Engaging with Carole Pateman</emph> (The Pennsylvania State University 2008). <emph type="i">See also</emph> T. Pogge, <emph type="i">The Role of International Law in Reproducing Massive Poverty</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Philosophy of International Law </emph>p. 445 (S. Besson &amp; J. Tasioulas eds., Oxford University 2010): “in so far as very poor people do consent, through a meaningfully democratic process, to some global institutional arrangements, the justificatory force of such consent is weakened by their having no other tolerable option, and weakened even further by the fact that their calamitous circumstances are partly due to those whose conduct this consent is meant to justify”.</p>
               </footnote> In many cases, when weaker states are denied the chance to wield significant influence over the process of regime formation and its outcomes, they are left with little choice but to follow suit.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_36" label="36.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>D. Bentley, <emph type="i">International Constraints on National Tax Policy</emph>, Tax Notes Intl. (2003), describing how international institutions have restricted the scope of fiscal choices available to developing nations and nations in distress; M. Stewart, <emph type="i">Global Trajectories of Tax Reform: The Discourse of Tax Reform in Developing and Transition Countries</emph>, 44 Harv. Intl. L. J. 1 (2003), short version in<emph type="i"> Critical Tax Theory: An Introduction</emph> (A.C. Infanti &amp; B.J. Crawford eds., Cambridge University 2009), mapping the influence of powerful states, experts and international institutions on national tax systems; A. Christians, <emph type="i">Global Trends and Constraints on Tax Policy in the Least Developed Countries</emph>, 42 U.B.C. L. Rev. 2, p. 241 (2010): “a series of inter-related global tax trends have indelibly altered the tax policy landscape and created significant constraints on the policy choices available to the least developed countries”.</p>
               </footnote> This lack of policy room is compounded when they are co-opted by technical discourses, which is notable in countries with limited administrative capacity due to the lack of human and economic resources.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_37" label="37.">
                  <p> This tactic is all but new. Historically, wealthier nations have always taken advantage of their privileged position to disseminate ideas, building “expert consensus”, with the help of international institutions under their control. <emph type="i">See </emph>M. Chossudovsky, <emph type="i">The Globalization of Poverty and the New World Order</emph> (2nd ed., Global Research 2003); N. Woods, <emph type="i">The Globalizers: The IMF, the World Bank and their Borrowers</emph> (Cornell University 2006); H.-J. Chang, <emph type="i">Bad Samaritans: The Guilty Secrets of Rich Nations and the Threat to Global Prosperity</emph> (Random House Business 2007); R. Peet, <emph type="i">Unholy Trinity: The IMF, World Bank and WTO</emph> (2nd ed., Zed Books 2009). For case studies on the role of external forces in shaping national tax reforms, <emph type="i">see</emph> M. Stewart, <emph type="i">Tax Policy Transfer to Developing Countries: Politics, Institutions and Experts</emph>, in <emph type="i">Global Debates about Taxation</emph> (H. Nehring &amp; F. Schui eds., Palgrave Macmillan 2007), with respect to Ghana; A. Christians, <emph type="i">Tax Treaties for Investment and Aid to Sub-Saharan Africa: A Case Study</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Effect of Treaties on Foreign Direct Investment: Bilateral Investment Treaties, Double Taxation Treaties, and Investment Flows</emph> (K.P. Sauvant &amp; L.E. Sachs eds., Oxford University 2009); M.A.M. Derzi &amp; A.M. Moreira, <emph type="i">Tax Reform and International Tax Norm Transmission: Case Study of Brazil – Value-Added Taxes</emph>, in <emph type="i">Separação de Poderes e Efetividade do Sistema Tributário</emph> (M.A.M. Derzi ed., Del Rey 2010); L. Ates, <emph type="i">Domestic Political Legitimacy of Tax Reform in Developing Countries: A Case Study of Turkey</emph>, 30 Wis. Int’l L. J. 3 (2012). For an overview, <emph type="i">see </emph>A. Christians, <emph type="i">Historic, Comparative and Evolutionary Analysis of Tax Systems</emph>, in <emph type="i">Separação de Poderes e Efetividade do Sistema Tributário</emph> (M.A.M. Derzi ed., Del Rey 2010). It is worth noting that this phenomenon is not limited to developing countries, but the difference is that developed countries have the ability to exert influence back. For a case study on Australia, <emph type="i">see</emph> D. Bentley, <emph type="i">Influence from the Shadows: The OECD, the Shape of Domestic Tax Policy and Lessons for Federal Systems</emph>, 13 Revenue L. J. 1 (2003).</p>
               </footnote> As a result, while no real inclusive platform for legitimate international tax law-making is made available, marginalized states “remain subjects of an invisible hand – not that of the market, but of expertise which denies its politics”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_38" label="38.">
                  <p> Kennedy, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_22">n. 22</xref>, at p. 24. <emph type="i">See also</emph> Fischer, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_15">n. 15</xref>, at pp. 3-4: “It might be one thing if the knowledge elites were able to handily dispose of the myriad of problems that confront contemporary societies. But we have come to learn over the past decades that the experts are themselves incapable of answering many of the pressing questions, at least with sufficient degrees of certainty, not to mention supplying workable solutions. To further dampen enthusiasm for such a politics we have also learned that scientific expertise is not the neutral, objective phenomenon that it has long purported to be. Indeed, professionals have all too often served the ideological function of legitimating decisions made elsewhere by political rather than scientific means”; H.-J. Chang, <emph type="i">Economics: The User’s Guide</emph> (Bloomsbury 2014): “Expert knowledge is absolutely necessary, but an expert by definition knows well only a narrow field and we cannot expect him or her to make a sound judgement on issues that involve more than one area of life (that is, most issues), balancing off different human needs, material constraints and ethical values. The possession of expert knowledge can sometimes give you a blinkered view. This dose of scepticism about expert knowledge should be applied to all areas of life, not just economics. But it is especially important in economics – a political argument often presented as a science”.</p>
               </footnote> Paraphrasing Ha-Joon Chang, international taxation is too important to be left to the pundits alone, whether they are economists, tax experts or even philosophers.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_39" label="39.">
                  <p> Chang, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_38">n. 38</xref>: “The economy is too important to be left to the professional economists alone”.</p>
               </footnote> Or, in the words of another renowned economist, Joseph Stiglitz:</p>
            <longquote>
               <p>There is a pretense that there are no trade-offs, and that, accordingly, decision making can be delegated to technocrats, who are assigned to the complex task of finding and managing the best economic system, and who are thought to be better equipped than politicians to make objective decisions. There are, of course, some problems which should be delegated to technocrats – like choosing the best computer system for running the social security <emph type="i">system</emph>. But delegating the writing of the rules of the economic game to technocrats can be justified only if there is a single best set of rules, one that makes everyone better off than any other set of rules. This is simply not the case; this view is not only wrong, but dangerous. With a few exceptions, there are always trade-offs. The existence of trade-offs means that there are choices to be made. It is only through the political system that those choices can be properly made, which is why it is so important to remedy the global democratic deficit.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_40" label="40.">
                     <p> J.E. Stiglitz, <emph type="i">Making Globalization Work</emph> p. 279 (W.W. Norton &amp; Company 2006).</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
            </longquote>
            <p>Seeing what is at stake, this is why it is so important to try to understand how the transnational order – as it exists today – restricts the flow of ideas and to pay attention to the impact such a restriction has on the process, as well as on the outcomes. </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_2_2" label="2.2.">
            <title>Power as a source of misrepresentation, or the problem of hegemony</title>
            <p>Contemporary structures of global tax governance are governed by the same international institutions that have been running the world within living memory. These are the Bretton Woods international financial institutions (IFIs), namely the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the World Bank (WB), the World Trade Organization (WTO), the United Nations (UN), but, above all, the OECD.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_41" label="41.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., J. Wouters &amp; K. Meuwissen, <emph type="i"><extxref target="hrte_p05_c13">Global Tax Governance: Work in Progress?</extxref></emph>, in<emph type="i"> Human Rights and Taxation in Europe and the World</emph> (G. Kofler, M.P. Maduro &amp; P. Pistone eds., IBFD 2011), Online Books IBFD. A complete list of global actors involved with tax issues would also include numerous regional institutions, but these have not had the same impact as the aforementioned. For an elaboration, <emph type="i">see </emph>Ring, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_25">n. 25</xref>.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>Notwithstanding the crucial role played by each of these institutions, it is the OECD that occupies a hegemonic, and for many years undisturbed, position in international taxation. The OECD gained prominence as a producer of international tax policy when the League of Nations was dissolved and replaced by the United Nations.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_42" label="42.">
                  <p> J.F.A. Jones, <emph type="i">Are Tax Treaties Necessary?</emph>, 53 Tax L. Rev. p. 2 (1999): “the OECD has taken [the] place [of the League of Nations] and is becoming the world body overseeing tax treaties”. <emph type="i">See also</emph> S. Jogarajan, <emph type="i">Prelude to the International Tax Treaty Network: 1845-1914 Early Tax Treaties and the Conditions for Action</emph>, 5 Oxford J. Legal Stud. 4 (2011); S. Jogarajan, <emph type="i"><extxref target="wtj_2013_03_int_1">Stamp, Seligman and the Drafting of the 1923 Experts’ Report on Double Taxation</extxref></emph>, 5 World Tax J. 3 (2013), Journals IBFD; L. Latulippe, <emph type="i">The Expansion of the Bilateral Tax Treaty Network in the 1990s: The OECD’s Role in the International Tax Coordination</emph>, 27 Austl. Tax F. (2012).</p>
               </footnote> It has, ever since, worked diligently to remain a hegemon in tax policy, framing global tax narratives and functioning as a de facto world tax organization.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_43" label="43.">
                  <p> The OECD takes pride in being a “market leader in developing standards and guidelines in the core of International Taxation”. OECD, <emph type="i">Current Tax Agenda</emph> p. 75 (OECD 2008) (file with the author). <emph type="i">See also </emph>A.J. Cockfield, <emph type="i">The Rise of the OECD as Informal ‘world tax organization’ through National Responses to E-Commerce Tax Challenges</emph>, 8 Yale J. L. &amp; Tech. 1, p. 186 (2006), concluding that “[t]he success of these efforts [to promote the taxation of international e-commerce] likely pre-empted national legislative and administrative actions as governments ... were generally content to abide by the OECD views”.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>Explanations for the OECD’s hegemony in the tax area point to the intimate relationship and consubstantiality between expertise and power.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_44" label="44.">
                  <p> As early as 1963, Nicholas Kaldor cautioned that national tax reform is not only a matter of expertise, but hinges on the concrete power of political actors. <emph type="i">See </emph>Kaldor, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_31">n. 31</xref>, at p. 418: </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>the advocacy of fiscal reform is not some magic potion that is capable of altering the balance of political power by stealth. No doubt, expert advice on tax reform can be very useful in making men of good will – ministers or officials – conscious of the precise nature of the legislative and administrative changes that are required. But what can actually be accomplished does not depend merely on the individual good will of ministers or on the correct intellectual appreciation of the technical problems involved. It is predominantly a matter of political power. </p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>What he had in mind at that time was the exercise of power within the boundaries of national territories. However, the same can be said in relation to international taxation and fiscal relations among countries: global powers also constraint national tax policy.</p>
               </footnote> Although this hegemonic position is partially attributed to the OECD’s unparalleled technical knowledge, its accumulated expertise is the direct result of substantial resources devoted by its wealthy members over the years to the Committee of Fiscal Affairs (CFA) and the Centre for Tax Policy and Administration (CTPA).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_45" label="45.">
                  <p> The CFA and CTPA are internal agencies that deal specifically with the development and global diffusion of tax standards and guidelines. For an analysis of how these groups develop tax norms, <emph type="i">see </emph>Christians, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_24">n. 24</xref>, at pp. 14-33. </p>
               </footnote> The power of the OECD stems from the fact that it groups the largest and most powerful economies in the world.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_46" label="46.">
                  <p> D.E. Spencer, <emph type="i">The United Nations: A Forum for Global Tax Issues?</emph>, 12 N.Z. J. Tax. L. &amp; Pol., p. 226 (2006): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>Historically, the OECD has been dominant in international tax issues because its members, the more industrialised countries, have exercised a major role in the world economy, with significant international trade and investment. Therefore, the OECD countries have had a greater interest in setting the rules for international tax issues, and for that purpose have given considerable resources to the OECD Department of Fiscal Affairs, whose technical expertise and studies are highly respected. </p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>
                     <emph type="i">See also</emph> Brauner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_27">n. 27</xref>, at p. 263, proposing a harmonized world tax regime, preferably led by the OECD, on the basis that it is “the most appropriate and practical institution around which a tax harmonization effort could be built, due to its expertise and experience in coordinating international tax cooperation”; H.J. Ault, <emph type="i">Reflections on the Role of the OECD in Developing International Tax Norms</emph>, 34 Brook. J. Intl. L. 3, p. 781 (2009), arguing that “[w]hile the OECD is certainly not a ‘Ruler of the World,’ by taking advantage of its expanded institutional structure and its high technical standards, going forward it seems to be well-placed to contribute to the development of international tax norms”; H.J. Ault, <emph type="i">Some Reflections on the OECD and the Sources of International Tax Principles</emph>, Tax Notes Intl., p. 1201 (2013), republished in R.S. Avi-Yonah ed., <emph type="i">International Tax Law</emph>, vol. 2 (Edward Elgar 2016): “If – and that is a big if – countries can agree within the framework of the OECD on what kinds of tax provisions are the legitimate exercise of tax sovereignty and which are ones that all would benefit from avoiding, the world would be a better place”; P.J. Ellingsworth, <emph type="i">International Tax in the 21st Century: The Role of the OECD</emph>, 61 Tax Executive 4, p. 279 (2009): “In the area of international tax, OECD Tax is the most objective and competent global organization”.</p>
               </footnote> After the 2007/8 economic crisis, the OECD became even more influential due to the support of the Group of Twenty (G20).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_47" label="47.">
                  <p> Wouters &amp; Meuwissen, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_41">n. 41</xref>, at pp. 222-227. <emph type="i">See also </emph>A. Christians, <emph type="i">Taxation in a Time of Crisis: Policy Leadership from the OECD to the G20</emph> (2010), 5 Nw. J. L. &amp; Soc. Poly. 1, p. 36, republished in R.S. Avi-Yonah ed., <emph type="i">International Tax Law</emph>, vol. 2 (Edward Elgar 2016): “The respective institutional capacities and roles of the G20 and the OECD suggest that the latter has a far greater role to play in developing tax policy ideas and bringing them to consensus positions, while the role of the former is in effect to syndicate those positions to a larger audience”; R. Eccleston, <emph type="i">The Dynamics of Global Economic Governance: The Financial Crisis, the OECD and the Politics of International Tax Cooperation</emph> p. 87 (Edward Elgar 2012), characterizing the relationship between the OECD and the G20 as symbiotic. </p>
               </footnote> Since then, it has expanded its agenda-setting role, to the point where today almost everything concerning international taxation policy is processed and filtered by its group of experts. In this sense, the OECD creates what some authors in international relations (IR) have termed an “epistemic community”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_48" label="48.">
                  <p> D. Ring, <emph type="i">International Tax Relations: Theory and Implications</emph>, 60 Tax L. Rev., pp. 110-112 (2007). <emph type="i">See also</emph> Christians, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_24">n. 24</xref>, at p. 22: “These [OECD] tax policy groups form an intertwined epistemic community that holds an important and influential position in the law-making order”. For the concept of epistemic communities, <emph type="i">see</emph> P.M. Haas ed., <emph type="i">Knowledge, Power, and International Policy Coordination</emph> (University of South Carolina 1997); M.K.D. Cross, <emph type="i">Rethinking Epistemic Communities Twenty Years Later</emph>, 39 Rev. Intl. Stud. 1 (2013).</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>Given that the OECD is accountable only to its members, who are mostly industrialized countries, it comes as no surprise that it is often described as a rich country’s club looking after the interests of the “Global North”. The self-interested nature of the OECD’s decision-making is confirmed by: (i) the ITR’s inbuilt distributive bias towards residence or capital-exporting countries; (ii) the resilience of outdated concepts and methods, such as the “permanent establishment” (PE) and separate entity taxation on the basis of the arm’s length standard (ALS) for transfer pricing (despite this being ineffective and exceedingly difficult for poor countries to administer);<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_49" label="49.">
                  <p> The OECD is known for vehemently rejecting alternative methods to income allocation, such as formulary apportionment, which could favour developing countries. <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., A. Christians, <emph type="i">Why Is the OECD So Afraid of Formulary Apportionment?</emph>, Tax, Society &amp; Culture (5 Feb. 2005), available at <url target="http://taxpol.blogspot.com.br/2015/02/why-is-oecd-so-afraid-of-formulary.html">http://taxpol.blogspot.com.br/2015/02/why-is-oecd-so-afraid-of-formulary.html</url>.</p>
               </footnote> and (iii) the difficulty of linking international tax with the development agenda.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_50" label="50.">
                  <p> D. Lesage, D. McNair &amp; M. Vermeiren, <emph type="i">From Monterrey to Doha: Taxation and Financing for Development</emph>, 28 Develop. Poly. Rev. 2, p. 157 (2010): “Notably, international institutions such as the UN, IMF, World Bank, and OECD, as well as academics, have remained relatively silent on this front, while governments have not mandated and resourced them to carry out more research”.</p>
               </footnote> Nevertheless, the ITR has been constantly presented as a natural product of a “remarkable consensus”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_51" label="51.">
                  <p> This wording has been employed by experts and international institutions to describe tax reform discourse amid developing and transition countries. Stewart, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_36">n. 36</xref>, at p. 356.</p>
               </footnote> or sometimes as a “flawed miracle”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_52" label="52.">
                  <p> R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">The Structure of International Taxation: A Proposal for Simplification</emph>, 74 Tex. L. Rev. 1301, p. 1303 (1996).</p>
               </footnote> Given that the majority of those affected by the ITR were not invited to participate in its initial formation and, to date, still remain excluded from decision-making processes, these descriptions both seem rather absurd.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_53" label="53.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>L.A. Sheppard, <emph type="i">Twilight of the International Consensus: How Multinationals Squandered Their Tax Privileges</emph>, 44 Wash. U. J. L. &amp; Pol’y 61, p. 62 (2014), short version <emph type="i">The Twilight of the International Consensus</emph>, Tax Analysts (2013): “[The international consensus] is a century-old, mostly European gentlemen’s agreement to give residence countries tax jurisdiction over income earned by their residents in source countries”. <emph type="i">See generally</emph> T. Dagan, <emph type="i">International Tax Policy: Between Competition and Cooperation </emph>(Cambridge University 2018).</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>Realizing the incongruity, some have tried to redefine the ITR in accordance with a theory of legal pluralism developed by Terence Halliday and Gregory Shaffer.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_54" label="54.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph> T.C. Halliday &amp; G. Shaffer, <emph type="i">Transnational Legal Orders</emph>, in <emph type="i">Transnational Legal Orders</emph> (T.C. Halliday &amp; G. Shaffer ed., Cambridge University 2015). </p>
               </footnote> Highlighting the presence of power asymmetries between nations, and the role of expert knowledge in shaping cross-border tax rules, Philipp Genschel and Thomas Rixen describe the ITR as a structure made up of not always compatible “transnational legal orders” (TLOs).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_55" label="55.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>P. Genschel &amp; T. Rixen, <emph type="i">Settling and Unsettling the Transnational Legal Order of International Taxation</emph>, in <emph type="i">Transnational Legal Orders</emph> (T.C. Halliday &amp; G. Shaffer ed., Cambridge University 2015). </p>
               </footnote> At their “solid institutional centre” is the OECD.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_56" label="56.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 155. </p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>According to Genschel and Rixen, TLOs in international taxation have two main objectives: to ensure double taxation relief and to curb tax competition. The original TLO dealt almost exclusively with double tax avoidance (DTA), while a new TLO emerged in the 1990s to address tax competition. Genschel and Rixen also explain that these two TLOs are interconnected. The way the ITR was designed initially, in order to provide double tax relief, triggered the pervasive problem of tax competition. In short, this ITR is therefore no miracle and it is certainly flawed. This notwithstanding, and except for piecemeal amendments,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_57" label="57.">
                  <p> In the 1960s, the US government unilaterally introduced anti-avoidance measures – the so-called controlled foreign corporation (CFC) rules – and then pressured other countries to do the same, so that US corporations would not have to face a competitive disadvantage. Genschel &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_55">n. 55</xref>, at p. 170. <emph type="i">See also</emph> R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">Constructive Unilateralism: U.S. Leadership and International Taxation</emph>, 1 U. Mich. Pub. Law &amp; Legal Theory, Research Paper n. 463 (University of Michigan 2015), available at 
                     <url target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2622868">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2622868</url>: “Initially, the adoption of Subpart F seemed to have put US-based multinationals at a competitive disadvantage, because no other country had such rules. But gradually this picture changed. [...] This is therefore a classic example of constructive unilateralism. The US led and others followed, and the end result is that most multinationals are subject to similar effective tax rates, with no competitive disadvantage or advantage”.</p>
               </footnote> the current “consensus” has remained almost unchanged because, despite its flaws, it still benefits OECD member countries.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_58" label="58.">
                  <p> Genschel &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_55">n. 55</xref>, at p. 169: “Although these states may be suffering from tax competition with tax havens, they benefit from the Model Convention’s residence-based rules on passive income in relation to <emph type="i">non</emph>-tax haven states. Because most states continue to be non-havens, and because many of these non-havens heavily import Western capital and technical know-how, Western states have a vested interest in preserving the TLO ... and closely related, Western states have an interest in preserving the OECD as the single and uncontested center of the TLO because doing so locks in their disproportionate influence over the contents of the TLO rules”.</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>For all these reasons, it may be more accurate to describe the current framework of international tax rules as a form of international fiscal imperialism.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_59" label="59.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>S.A. Rocha, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2014_02_br_1">International Fiscal Imperialism and the “Principle” of the Permanent Establishment</extxref></emph>, 68 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 2 (2014), Journals IBFD; Antón, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_3">n. 3</xref>.</p>
               </footnote> Countries have been pressured to conform to international standards fixed by the OECD.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_60" label="60.">
                  <p> The 1998 OECD’s initiative that attempted to incriminate what it deemed to be “harmful” tax practices is a case in point.<emph type="i"> See</emph>, e.g., K.B. Brown, <emph type="i">Harmful Tax Competition: The OECD View</emph>, 32 Geo. Wash. J. Int’l L. &amp; Econ. (1999); A. Townsend Jr., <emph type="i">Global Schoolyard Bully: The Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development’s Coercive Efforts to Control Tax Competition</emph>, 25 Fordham Int’l L. J. 215 (2001); V.E. James, <emph type="i">Twenty-First Century Pirates of the Caribbean: How the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development Robbed Fourteen CARICOM Countries of Their Tax and Economic Policy Sovereignty</emph>, 34 U. Miami Inter-American L. Rev. 1 (2002); K. Carlson, <emph type="i">When Cows Have Wings: An Analysis of the OECD’s Tax Haven as It Relates to Globalization, Sovereignty and Privacy</emph>, 35 J. Marshall L. Rev. 163 (2002); R. Sanders, <emph type="i">The Fight Against Fiscal Colonialism: The OECD and Small Jurisdictions</emph>, 365 The Round Table (2002); J.C. Sharman, <emph type="i">Havens in a Storm: The Global Struggle for Tax Regulation</emph> (Cornell University 2006); S. Jogarajan &amp; M. Stewart, <emph type="i">Harmful Tax Competition: Defeat or Victory?</emph>, 22 Australian Tax Forum (2007); R.T. Kudrle, <emph type="i">The OECD’s Harmful Tax Competition Initiative and the Tax Havens: From Bombshell to Damp Squib</emph>, 8 Global Econ. J. 1 (2008).</p>
               </footnote> Fully understanding how international tax relations are structured entails holding a critical view of current practices of global tax governance.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_61" label="61.">
                  <p> Global governance in general – but not global <emph type="i">tax</emph> governance in particular – has already been extensively interrogated and problematized by critical legal scholars, following the leading work of Professor David Trubek of the University of Wisconsin Law School. <emph type="i">See generally </emph>G. de Búrca, C. Kilpatrick &amp; J. Scott eds., <emph type="i">Critical Legal Perspectives on Global Governance: Liber Amicorum David M. Trubek</emph> (Hart 2014). </p>
               </footnote> It is only by doing so that one can grasp the real nature of the ITR, or tax TLOs, namely, international arrangements essentially based on relations of unequal power.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_62" label="62.">
                  <p> D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">Law and the Political Economy of the World</emph>, in <emph type="i">Critical Legal Perspectives on Global Governance: Liber Amicorum David M. Trubek</emph> p. 95 (G. de Búrca, C. Kilpatrick &amp; J. Scott eds., Hart 2014), attributing to international legal scholarship the role of contributing to “situat[e] international law in the larger global political and economic system, interpreting its role as the glue linking leading and lagging ideas, regions, or economic sectors, or as the cloak hiding asymmetric dynamics of power in political economy of the world”; Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_21">n. 21</xref>, at pp. 331: “The task for international lawyers is not to learn new managerial vocabularies but to use the language of international law to articulate the politics of critical universalism”.</p>
               </footnote> Pursuing such a critical project reveals that, in order to bring about a more just world order, the first step is to come to terms with these power dynamics, gaining more insight into who wields political authority in the global tax space.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_63" label="63.">
                  <p> D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">The Mystery of Global Governance</emph>, in <emph type="i">Ruling the World? Constitutionalism, International Law, and Global Governance</emph> p. 38 (J.L. Dunoff &amp; J.P. Trachtman eds., Cambridge University 2009): “If we understood the machinery by which inequalities and hierarchies of influence and wealth and knowledge are reproduced, we might know how to make the world a better place”.</p>
               </footnote> What these dynamics indicate is that input from the majority of the world’s population is persistently excluded from impacting the processes of policy setting, thereby perpetuating historical patterns of economic domination and exploitation.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_64" label="64.">
                  <p>
                     <emph type="i"> See </emph>Forst, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_7">n. 7</xref>, at pp. 256-257, arguing that “the discussion of principles of transnational justice is to start from an analysis of the present global context of <emph type="i">injustice</emph>”, which “must be viewed as one of a complex system of power and domination with a variety of powerful actors, from international institutions to transnational corporations, local elites, and so forth”. More than that, it is only by “[e]xercising our critical muscles, [that] we can discourage being carried away by the dream of universal values”. D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">Preface</emph>, in <emph type="i">New Approaches to International Law: The European and the American Experience</emph> p. xi (J.M. Beneyto &amp; D. Kennedy eds., Springer 2012). </p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3" label="3.">
         <title>Alternatives to Our “Club Model” of Global Tax Governance: The Problem of CO<sub>2</sub></title>
         <p>During the past decades, a series of proposals for reforming the ITR has been advanced by prominent public figures, who have either called for the creation of a stand-alone ITO or for the strengthening of existing international cooperation forums. Among these have been:<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_65" label="65.">
               <p> Spencer, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_46">n. 46</xref>, at pp. 224-227.</p>
            </footnote> Vito Tanzi, former IMF economist; the late Kofi Annan, former UN Secretary-General; Ernesto Zedillo, former Mexican President; Frances Horner, former OECD staff; and the late tax law professor Michael McIntyre, former consultant to the UN Committee of Experts on International Cooperation in Tax Matters. More recently, some scholars in tax and other areas have re-examined these ideas in a new light, trying to provide philosophical and economic justifications for global tax reform.</p>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_1" label="3.1.">
            <title>The rise and fall of the ITO and the forgotten problem of power</title>
            <p>The first systematic proposal for the creation of an International Tax Organization (ITO) came in 1999 from Vito Tanzi, an Italian economist known for the so-called “Oliveira-Tanzi effect”. Following his previous work on the impact of the process of liberalization of markets and economic integration on national tax systems,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_66" label="66.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">Taxation in an Integrating World</emph> (Brookings Institution 1995), discussing the development of opportunities for tax avoidance and evasion that make it ever more difficult for states to maintain high levels of taxation, let alone progressivity. Tanzi ended this book with the following statement (<emph type="i">see </emph>p. 141): “There is no world institution with the responsibility to establish desirable rules for taxation and with enough clout to induce countries to follow those rules. Perhaps the time has come to establish one”. <emph type="i">See also </emph>V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">Globalization, Technological Developments, and the Work of Fiscal Termites</emph>, 26 Brook. J. Intl. L. 4 (2001), outlining (at least) eight “fiscal termites” that can corrode the tax bases of nation-states: electronic commerce and transactions; use of electronic money; intra-company trade; offshore financial centres and tax haven; derivatives and hedge funds; inability to tax financial capital; growing foreign activities; and foreign shopping.</p>
               </footnote> Tanzi stated that negative externalities and spillovers were being created and/or aggravated as a result of deepening globalization. This scenario, he argued, called for a global solution. The world was in need of an ITO, not for collecting taxes, but to deal effectively with a series of tax-related technical problems.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_67" label="67.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph> V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">Is There a Need for a World Tax Organization?</emph>, in <emph type="i">The Economics of Globalization: Policy Perspectives from Public Economics</emph> (A. Razin &amp; E. Sadka eds., Cambridge University 1999); V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">The Future of Fiscal Federalism and the Need for Global Government: A Reply to Roland Vaubel</emph>, 25 Euro. J. Polit. Econ. 1 (2008); V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">Lakes, Oceans, and Taxes: Why the World Needs a World Tax Authority</emph>, in <emph type="i">Global Tax Fairness</emph> (T. Pogge &amp; K. Mehta eds., Oxford University 2016). </p>
               </footnote> These included: (i) locating global trends and problems in the area of tax policy, in the same way as the OECD’s CFA has done for its member countries; (ii) collecting fiscal statistical data and making them available to as many countries as possible, following the IMF’s and the OECD’s works; (iii) periodically releasing “World Tax Development Reports”; (iv) maintaining surveillance of tax developments, in the same way as the IMF monitors macroeconomic policy; (v) helping countries coordinate or even harmonize their tax systems, in the same way as the IMF provides technical assistance; (vi) producing global tax standards; (vii) serving as an international tax forum for policymakers and experts; and (viii) serving as an international tax arbitral tribunal for solving disputes between countries.</p>
            <p>In 2000, Kofi Annan presented a report to the Preparatory Committee for the UN project on Financing for Development (FfD), recommending a careful in-depth study on the viability of an ITO.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_68" label="68.">
                  <p> United Nations, General Assembly, <emph type="i">Report of the Secretary-General to the Preparatory Committee for the High-Level International Intergovernmental Event on Financing for Development</emph>, A/AC.257/12 (UN 2000) [hereinafter <emph type="i">Annan Report</emph>].</p>
               </footnote> This study was to be conducted along with the IMF and other IFIs. In Annan’s own words, an ITO “could provide a global forum for the discussion of and cooperation in tax matters, including the sharing of national taxation experiences; the development of definitions, standards and norms for tax policy, administration and related matters; the identification of national tax trends and problems; tax reporting; and the provision of technical assistance to national tax authorities, particularly those of developing and transition economy countries”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_69" label="69.">
                  <p> Id., at pp. 51-52.</p>
               </footnote> He went further and appointed the economist Ernesto Zedillo as chair of the High-Level Panel on FfD. In its recommendations, the panel briefly mentioned the possibility of creating an ITO.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_70" label="70.">
                  <p> United Nations, General Assembly, <emph type="i">Report of the High-Level Panel on Financing for Development</emph>, A/55/1000 (UN 2001) [hereinafter <emph type="i">Zedillo Report</emph>].</p>
               </footnote> Twice making express reference to Tanzi’s article,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_71" label="71.">
                  <p> Id., at pp. 28 n. 4 and 65 n. 24.</p>
               </footnote> the Zedillo Report listed six potential benefits of having an ITO: (1) to collect statistical data, pinpoint trends and problems, generate reports, offer technical assistance and produce global standards in the area of tax policy and administration; (2) to maintain surveillance of tax developments, in the same way as the IMF monitors macroeconomic policy; (3) to curb tax competition; (4) to develop arbitration procedures; (5) to take up the OECD’s project on information exchange in tax matters, developing multilateral mechanisms for curtailing tax evasion; and (6) to promote unitary taxation with formulary apportionment.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_72" label="72.">
                  <p> Id., at pp. 6-7, 28 and 65. For a defence of Zedillo’s proposal and an argument for why the United States should have supported the ITO, <emph type="i">see</emph> W. Whisenhunt, <emph type="i">To Zedillo or not to Zedillo: Why the World Needs an ITO</emph>, 16 Temp. Int’l Comp. L. J. 541 (2002).</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>One of the most important articles defending the creation of the ITO was written by Horner, after leaving the OECD, where she was responsible for the projects on tax competition and transfer pricing guidelines.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_73" label="73.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph> F.M. Horner, <emph type="i">Do We Need an International Tax Organization?</emph>, Tax Notes Intl. (2001).</p>
               </footnote> Her arguments are interesting because they give special emphasis to the need to include developing countries in global tax discourse. Criticizing the other proposals for not giving priority to the concerns of developing countries, and going against those who said an ITO would be redundant, Horner claimed that “a new global institution in taxation policy will make a significant, non-redundant contribution to global governance if – and only if – it gives a full and true voice to the fiscal concerns and needs of developing countries”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_74" label="74.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 179.</p>
               </footnote> According to her proposal, five conditions were essential for an international tax arrangement to be valuable: (1) “no gag rules: all issues must be eligible for discussion at the forum”; (2) “fair share: attention should be given to profit allocation rules”; (3) “link to official development assistance: development issues should be relevant in formulating tax policy”; (4) “tax administration efficiency: developed countries should assist developing countries in improving tax administration”; and (5) “governance: developing countries should have a meaningful voice in any world tax”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_75" label="75.">
                  <p> Id., at pp. 185-187.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>A 2003 report by the UN Ad Hoc Group of Experts on International Cooperation in Tax Matters, assisted by Professor McIntyre, also discussed the need to give developing and transitional countries a seat at the table.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_76" label="76.">
                  <p> United Nations, Secretariat, Ad Hoc Group of Experts on International Cooperation in Tax Matters, <emph type="i">Institutional Framework for International Tax Cooperation</emph>, ST/SG/AC.8/2003/L.6 (UN 2003) [hereinafter <emph type="i">McIntyre Report</emph>].</p>
               </footnote> The McIntyre Report called for a new institutional framework built upon the UN framework, but restructured “to serve the needs of developing and transitional countries for assistance and support on international tax matters”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_77" label="77.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 14.</p>
               </footnote> The proposal sought to transform the existing UN Ad Hoc Group from an expert group to an intergovernmental commission with an independent budget, whose central goal would be “to give the developing and transitional countries an effective voice when issues of cooperation on tax matters are being decided by the international community”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_78" label="78.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 15.</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>Despite all these efforts, the proposed ITO never took root. The main reason is political power: the OECD actively lobbied the G7 against the ITO.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_79" label="79.">
                  <p> V. Tanzi, <emph type="i">Globalisation and Coordination of Fiscal Policies</emph>, Proceedings of a Conference Organized by the School of International Studies, University of Trento, Working Paper 03/2004 11 (University of Trento 2004).</p>
               </footnote> In addition, the OECD, joining forces with two Bretton Woods institutions (the IMF and World Bank), managed to find a substitute for an ITO, which they called the International Tax Dialogue (ITD). The ITD platform is neither an international institution nor a global forum for negotiation and cooperation.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_80" label="80.">
                  <p> Lesage, McNair &amp; Vermeiren, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_50">n. 50</xref>, at p. 164. </p>
               </footnote> Instead, it is better described as a “networked governance”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_81" label="81.">
                  <p> D. Lesage, <emph type="i">Global Taxation Governance after the 2002 UN Monterrey Conference</emph>, 36 Oxford Develop. Stud. 3, p. 288 (2008). </p>
               </footnote> The ITD was created in April 2002 with the declared purpose of collecting and sharing tax information, and promoting technical debate on tax-related issues. Its creation reveals the desire of the three IOs, the OECD key among them, to retain control of the international tax agenda.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_82" label="82.">
                  <p> Curiously, the BEPS Project can be seen as the latest attempt of the OECD “to reclaim relevance” in international taxation. <emph type="i">See </emph>Sheppard, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_53">n. 53</xref>, at p. 62. </p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>To sum up, except maybe for Horner’s proposals, none of the aforementioned proposals were explicitly dedicated to providing a strong justification for an inclusive political forum that could empower developing countries. Nor was the need to put the global tax debate into a wider perspective – e.g. including developmental and other interests of poor nations – seriously considered. Most of the proposals were formulated on the assumption that the major fiscal problems facing countries today are technical, leaving the power problem in international tax relations unanswered. As Horner herself writes, “[f]or the developing countries of the world, taxation policy and the development agenda are inseparable” and “rich countries make a serious mistake when they act globally to address either one of these issues on a stand-alone basis”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_83" label="83.">
                  <p> Horner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_73">n. 73</xref>, at p. 179.</p>
               </footnote> Consequently, “[d]eveloping countries might judge the sincerity of any global tax cooperation effort by reference to how many of these key issues are open to discussion and how many are ‘off the table’”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_84" label="84.">
                  <p> Id.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_2" label="3.2.">
            <title>New proposals for international tax cooperation: Expertise and power, one more time</title>
            <p>More recently, the idea of enhancing tax cooperation among countries has been reintroduced in academic circles. First, three political theorists, Thomas Rixen, Peter Dietsch and Douglas Bamford, have initiated a discussion on the principles of international tax justice that should be enforced by an adjudicating ITO, modelled on the WTO’s Dispute Settlement System (DSS). Second, three tax scholars, H. David Rosenbloom, Noam Noked and Mohamed S. Helal, have put forward a new proposal for international tax cooperation, one that is different from an ITO.</p>
            <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_2_1" label="3.2.1.">
               <title>Who actually needs an international tax court?<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_2_1_fn1" label="*"><p>See ITO, op. cit.</p></footnote></title>
               <p>The idea of an ITO has captivated not only economists, tax scholars and public authorities; lately, it has also caught the attention of academics interested in the topic of global tax justice. </p>
               <p>The political economist Rixen was the first to address this issue. He began to make the case for an ITO in his work on the relationship between tax competition and the rise of inequality. In his early work on this subject, Rixen argued for an institutionalist view of tax competition, according to which the problem of under – or no taxation – should be seen as nothing more than an (unintended) by-product of the DTA regime set up in the 1920s and 1930s.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_85" label="85.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See</emph> T. Rixen, <emph type="i">From Double Tax Avoidance to Tax Competition: Explaining the Institutional Trajectory of International Tax Governance</emph>, 18 Rev. Int’l Pol. Econ. 2 (2010). <emph type="i">See also </emph>A.H. Rosenzweig, <emph type="i">Why Are There Tax Havens?</emph>, 52 William &amp; Mary L. Rev. 923, pp. 928-929, contending that tax havens are “a symptom of the unintentional incentives created and perpetuated by the modern international tax regime embodied in the laws of countries such as the United States”.</p>
                  </footnote> Thereafter, Rixen used economic analysis and social contract theory to demonstrate that the phenomenon of tax competition – including tax evasion and avoidance – is fundamentally unjust, because it causes inequality between and across borders.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_86" label="86.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See</emph> T. Rixen, <emph type="i">Tax Competition and Inequality: The Case for Global Tax Governance</emph>, 17 Glob. Governance (2011).</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>According to Rixen, tax competition undermines the integrity of tax jurisdictions and the state’s capacity to promote a particular conception of justice through redistributive taxation. As a possible solution to this global issue, he has advocated a system of global tax governance under an ITO. He proposes a supranational organization that would be entrusted with lawmaking and enforcement powers, sanctioning governments that engage in tax competition. Its main function would be to administer a regime of unitary taxation with formulary apportionment (UT+FA), but Rixen conceded that it could also serve as a forum for multilateral negotiations, so that countries could reach agreement on a common consolidated corporate tax base. </p>
               <p>Rixen acknowledged that the only way to secure maximum inclusion would be for the ITO to operate under the institutional framework of the United Nations, but he considered this to be an idealistic scenario.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_87" label="87.">
                     <p> Id., at pp. 459 and 461: “the ITO should ideally be under the auspices of the United Nations”; “the successful implementation of UT+FA should be undertaken by an international tax organization that would ideally operate under the auspices of the UN”.</p>
                  </footnote> Presumably, the need for an ITO would still be valid even if separate from the United Nations. Its priority would be to put an end to tax competition, even in the absence of a universal consensus on the appropriate allocation formula for the division of the global tax base.</p>
               <p>Working subsequently with philosopher Peter Dietsch, Rixen sought to elaborate on the substantive principles of “global background justice”<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_88" label="88.">
                     <p> They take this concept from Miriam Ronzoni, who expands globally John Rawls’s idea of “background justice”, i.e. a set of necessary conditions for justice. Compare M. Ronzoni, <emph type="i">The Global Order: A Case of Background Injustice? A Practice-Dependent Account</emph>, 37 Philo. &amp; Pub. Affairs. 3 (2009), with J. Rawls, <emph type="i">Political Liberalism</emph> sec. 4, “The Importance of Background Justice” (2nd ed., Columbia University 2005).</p>
                  </footnote> as a means to guide international taxation as a normative matter.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_89" label="89.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See </emph>Dietsch &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">Tax Competition and Global Background Justice</emph>, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>; Dietsch &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">Redistribution, Globalisation, and Multi-Level Governance</emph>,<emph type="i"> supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>.</p>
                  </footnote> Dietsch and Rixen begin by trying to demonstrate why some fiscal activities are problematic from a universal viewpoint, as though all the countries in the world could, or should, concur in rejecting tax competition. Relying again on empirical studies, Dietsch and Rixen reiterate that curbing harmful tax practices would be in the interest of all states, because of its effects on exacerbating social inequalities – especially among developing countries, which are seen by some as the biggest losers in tax competition.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_90" label="90.">
                     <p> Developed countries, so the argument goes, lose out on their capacity to redistribute, but get to maintain their ability to raise revenue by adopting “tax cut cum base broadening” measures; as for developing countries, whose tax systems are unstable, losses would include both components. Notably, this argument in particular depends almost exclusively on a 2004 study that revealed a<emph type="i"> stronger</emph> decline in developing countries’ tax revenues. However, as the authors of that study warned in the end: “[t]he results reported here are preliminary. They may be contaminated by data inaccuracies or incompleteness of country coverage or reflect the dates chosen for the comparisons. The first lesson is that, even more than usual, more work is needed to confirm the story beginning to emerge”. M. Keen &amp; A. Simone, <emph type="i">Is Tax Competition Harming Developing Countries More Than Developed?</emph>, Tax Notes Int’l, p. 1325 (2004). It is worth noting that some authors have doubted that tax competition is that problematic. <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g. J. Roin, <emph type="i">Competition and Evasion: Another Perspective on International Tax Competition</emph>, 89 Geo. L. J. 543 (2001); Y. Margalioth, <emph type="i">Tax Competition, Foreign Direct Investments and Growth: Using the Tax System to Promote Developing Countries</emph>, 23 Va. Tax Rev. 161 (2003); M. Littlewood, <emph type="i">Tax Competition: Harmful to Whom?</emph>, Mich. J. Int’l L. 411 (2004); J. Douglas Wilson &amp; D.E. Wildasin, <emph type="i">Capital Tax Competition: Bane or Boon</emph>, 88 J. Pub. Econ. (2004); A.P. Morriss &amp; M. Lota, <emph type="i">Cartelizing Taxes: Understanding the OECD’s Campaign against ‘Harmful Tax Competition’</emph>, 4 Colum. J. Tax L. 1 (2012); P. Penteado Neto, <emph type="i">International Trade Subsidy Rules and Tax and Financial Export Incentives: From Limitations on Fiscal Sovereignty to Development-Inducing Mechanisms </emph>(AuthorHouse 2012); P. Genschel &amp; L. Seelkopf, <emph type="i">Winners and Losers of Tax Competition</emph>, in <emph type="i">Global Tax Governance: What Is Wrong with It and How to Fix It</emph> (P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen eds., ECPR 2016); Dagan, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_53">n. 53</xref>; L.V. Faulhaber, <emph type="i">The Trouble with Tax Competition: From Practice to Theory</emph>, 71 Tax L. Rev. (2018).</p>
                  </footnote> Perhaps the first question that would arise in this context is: what are these developing countries that (sometimes without even knowing it) are being harmed by engaging in tax competition?<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_91" label="91.">
                     <p> Part of this argument relies, as noted by Diane Ring, on a problematic assumption that countries that engage in tax competition are necessarily in error, because they wrongly think “the benefits from competition outweigh forgone revenue, either because the benefits of that investment to the state were low or because business was likely to choose to invest in that state for other reasons”. D. Ring, <emph type="i">Democracy, Sovereignty and Tax Competition: The Role of Tax Sovereignty in Shaping Tax Cooperation</emph>, 9 Fla. Tax Rev. 5, p. 566 (2009). But<emph type="i"> see </emph>H. Kelsen, <emph type="i">Absolutism and Relativism in Philosophy and Politics</emph>, in <emph type="i">What is Justice? Justice, Law, and Politics in the Mirror of Science: Collected Essays by Hans Kelsen</emph> (Lawbook Exchange 2013): “This belief [in absolute values] irresistibly – and has always – led to a situation in which the one who assumes to possess the secret to the absolute good claims to have the right to impose his opinion as well as his will upon the others who are in error. And to be in error is, according to this view, to be wrong, and hence punishable”.</p>
                  </footnote> This is not to deny that tax competition should be a matter of concern.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_92" label="92.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">Globalization, Tax Competition, and the Fiscal Crisis of the Welfare State</emph>, 113 Harv. L. Rev. 7 (2000); R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">Globalization and Tax Competition: Implications for Developing Countries</emph>, 74 Cepal Rev./Law Quadrangle Notes (2001); R.S. Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">Bridging the North/South Divide: International Redistribution and Tax Competition</emph>, 26 Mich. J. Int’l L. 371 (2004); P. Dietsch, <emph type="i">Catching Capital: The Ethics of Tax Competition</emph> (Oxford University 2015). </p>
                  </footnote> Yet we should not overstate the importance of economic analysis, drawing conclusions without first consulting with the affected parties.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_93" label="93.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See</emph> Chang, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_38">n. 38</xref>: “If there is no one right answer in economics, then we cannot leave it to the experts alone”; W. Easterly, <emph type="i">The Tyranny of Experts: Economists, Dictators, and the Forgotten Rights of the Poor</emph> (Basic Books 2013), disputing development experts’ and autocrats’ attempts to help poor countries and implying that they might do more harm than good; W. Easterly, <emph type="i">The Tyranny of Experts: Foreign Aid versus Freedom for the World’s Poor</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Economics of International Development: Foreign Aid versus Freedom of the World’s Poor</emph> (W. Easterly et al., IEA 2016): “if you thought that problems of poverty could be solved by expert solutions and by experts, there were already experts in 1938 that already knew the answers. It did not work then and it’s not working now”.</p>
                  </footnote> The degree to which tax competition should be addressed and how this should be done are both issues that must be addressed democratically among all countries involved, and not solely by specialists in their ivory towers.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_94" label="94.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See </emph>J. Dewey, <emph type="i">The Public and Its Problems: An Essay in Political Inquiry</emph> pp. 154-155 (M.L. Rogers ed., The Pennsylvania State University 2012): “No government by experts in which the masses do not have the chance to inform the experts as to their needs can be anything but an oligarchy managed in the interests of the few”; T. Piketty, <emph type="i">Capital in the Twenty-First Century</emph> (A. Goldhammer trans., The Belknap Press of Harvard University 2014): “Democracy will never be supplanted by a republic of experts – and that is a very good thing”.</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>More importantly, does it even make sense, politically speaking, to divide a highly pluralistic world that is dominated by a multiplicity of interests<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_95" label="95.">
                     <p> Our world is better described as a <emph type="i">pluriversum</emph>, instead of a <emph type="i">universum</emph>. <emph type="i">See</emph> N. Krisch, <emph type="i">Beyond Constitutionalism: The Pluralist Structure of Postnational Law</emph> (Oxford University 2010), developing a pluralist model of postnational governance; A.V. Teixeira, <emph type="i">Teoria Pluriversalista do Direito Internacional</emph> (WMF Martins Fontes 2011), developing a pluriversalistic theory of international law; J.L. Cohen, G<emph type="i">lobalization and Sovereignty: Rethinking Legality, Legitimacy, and Constitutionalism</emph> pp. 21 and 269 (Cambridge University 2012): “We still inhabit a global pluri-verse of 193 sovereign states whose political cultures, organizational principles, conceptions of justice, and domestic legitimacy are diverse and at times in conflict with one another”; G. de Búrca, R.O. Keohane &amp; C. Sabel, <emph type="i">New Modes of Pluralist Global Governance</emph>, 45 N.Y.U. J Int’l L. &amp; Pol. 723 (2013), arguing for a model of experimentalist governance, in order to enhance the understanding of global pluralism in law and politics. Compare Schmitt, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13">n. 13</xref>, at p. 53 (“The political world is a pluriverse, not a universe”), with C. Mouffe, <emph type="i">Agonistics: Thinking the World Politically</emph> (Verso 2013) (enquiring “about the implications of seeing the world as a pluri-verse”, and asserting that “[t]o take account of the political in its antagonistic dimension requires acknowledging that the world is a pluri-verse, not a universe”; “[t]he world is a pluri-verse, not a universe, and the Western model represents only one possible political form of life among others”; “[h]ere again I agree with Schmitt that the world is a pluri-verse, not a universe”).</p>
                  </footnote> into these two extremely broad categories (developed and developing countries)?<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_96" label="96.">
                     <p> It is possible to think of (<emph type="i">at least</emph>) four groups of states, sorted out by similar positions concerning tax competition: (1) “OECD member states eager to limit tax competition”; (2) “OECD member states engaging in competitive behavior”; (3) “non-OECD states that feel ‘forced’ to engage in tax competition to secure significant, nonmobile business investment (<emph type="i">e.g.</emph> manufacturing, production, <emph type="i">etc.</emph>)”; (4) “non-OECD members engaged in tax competition over mobile financial and other activities”. Ring, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_91">n. 91</xref>, at pp. 563-567. Many other types of divisions are conceivable, as between rich and poor tax havens, high-tax and low-tax countries, countries that tax more consumption than income and vice versa, countries that have other sources of tax revenue, and so on.</p>
                  </footnote> 
               </p>
               <p>Expanding their initial analysis, Dietsch and Rixen introduce the notion of fiscal self-determination (or tax sovereignty) as something at stake. Tax competition, they contend, undermines the de facto sovereignty of states by putting competitive pressure on domestic fiscal regimes. In order to counter this problem and ensure effective fiscal sovereignty, they provide two universal principles of tax justice. The first is the so-called principle of membership, which holds that “[n]atural and legal persons should be liable to pay tax in the state of which they are a member”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_97" label="97.">
                     <p> Dietsch &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">Tax Competition and Global Background Justice</emph>, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>, at p. 158.</p>
                  </footnote> The second is that of fiscal constraint, a much more complex idea, requiring an evaluation of the legitimacy of each countries’ tax practices on a case-by-case basis. To accomplish the latter goal, they consider, and then reject, two possible strategies: an outcome-based constraint<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_98" label="98.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 162: “A tax policy is legitimate if it does not produce a collectively suboptimal outcome. A collectively suboptimal outcome is here defined as one where the aggregate extent of fiscal self-determination of states is reduced”. </p>
                  </footnote> and an intention-based constraint.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_99" label="99.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 162: “Rather than trying to delineate legitimate fiscal interdependence from illegitimate tax competition by appeal to outcomes, an alternative strategy is to focus on the intention that motivates the tax policy in question”. </p>
                  </footnote> Since the first would leave little room for states to exercise their tax sovereignty and the second would overshoot the target by banning policies that supposedly benefit everyone (e.g. investments in infrastructure and human capital), they conclude that the most appropriate criterion would be a mixed constraint: “a tax policy is legitimate if it does not produce a collectively suboptimal outcome, that is, a negative impact on the aggregate extent of fiscal self-determination”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_100" label="100.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 164.</p>
                  </footnote> To illustrate, Table 1 summarizes what is prohibited and what is allowed under the mixed constraint:<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_101" label="101.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 165.</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <emph type="b">Table 1 – A mixed constraint on fiscal policy</emph>
               </p>
               <table>
                  <tgroup cols="4">
                     <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="2122*"/>
                     <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2122*"/>
                     <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2122*"/>
                     <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2122*"/>
                     <thead><row>
                           <entry colname="col1"/>
                           <entry colname="col2"/>
                           <entry align="center" nameend="col4" namest="col3">
                              <p>
                                 Outcome
                              </p>
                           </entry>
                        </row><row>
                           <entry colname="col1"/>
                           <entry colname="col2"/>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>
                                 Good</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col4">
                              <p>
                                 Bad
                              </p>
                           </entry>
                        </row></thead><tbody>
                        
                        
                        
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>
                                 <emph type="b">Intent</emph>
                              </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>Independent</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>1</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col4">
                              <p>2</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row><row>
                           <entry colname="col1"/>
                           <entry colname="col2"/>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>✓</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col4">
                              <p>✓</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1"/>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>Strategic</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>3</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col4">
                              <p>4</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1"/>
                           <entry colname="col2"/>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>✓</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col4">
                              <p>✗</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                     </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
               </table>
               <p>Hence, a state would only be forbidden from exercising its tax sovereignty in cases where it has been proven that its tax system was strategically designed to lure capital from another state, and if this leads to a bad overall outcome. To institutionalize these principles of international tax justice, Dietsch and Rixen call for the creation of an ITO. This would have to be an inclusive supranational institution that is capable of providing a level playing field for all states, so that they can negotiate the rules of the international tax game. To ensure the agreed rules are followed, it should also be powerful enough to enforce them. For that reason, they model their proposal after the Dispute Settlement Body (DSB) of the WTO, which allows for the imposition of economic sanctions on non-compliant countries.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_102" label="102.">
                     <p> One last thing that deserves attention is that, as Dietsch and Rixen make clear, their proposal would depend on the establishment of an effective system of multilateral automatic exchange of information. (<emph type="i">See </emph>id. at 167.) They do not discuss, however, the costs associated with the implementation of such a system, especially for developing countries, many of which do not even have income taxation as their main source of revenue. <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., P. Rosenblatt, <emph type="i">General Anti-Avoidance Rules for Major Developing Countries</emph> (Wolters Kluwer 2015): </p>
                     <longquote>
                        <p>Generally, developed countries have broad-based taxes. Direct taxes, particularly personal income and social contributions, and less corporate income – are responsible for most revenue. Indirect taxes represent a smaller share of the tax collection, especially on domestic consumption rather than on international trade. Developing countries have a very different tax structure. Indirect taxes are their main source of revenue, for they are “easy-to-collect”, have fewer administrative costs and are less sophisticated. Import tariffs and excises – particularly resource taxes – still play an important role. Seigniorage or inflation tax, although not a proper tax, is often high. Income tax is a minor source of revenue given its narrow tax base, high collection costs and ease of evasion by the self-employed. The tax base consists mainly of taxpayers who are subject to withholding taxes on wages, mainly of the public sector, and large businesses that depend on the finance sector and comply with accounting requirements. This structure has a great distorting economic effect as opposed to modern taxes. </p>
                     </longquote>
                     <p>
                        <emph type="i">See also</emph> Genschel &amp; Seelkopf, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_31">n. 31</xref>.</p>
                  </footnote> 
               </p>
               <p>In adjudicating tax disputes, Dietsch and Rixen would have the ITO reviewing national tax laws through the application of not only legal reasoning, but also (and most controversially) economic reasoning, in order to decide whether a specific fiscal policy should be prohibited under the terms of the proposed regime. But as legal scholars and practitioners are well aware, the act of interpretation is also an act of creation.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_103" label="103.">
                     <p> This was already clear to Hans Kelsen almost a century ago, as well as to H.H.H. Kelsen, <emph type="i">Introduction to the Problems of Legal Theory</emph> pp. 77 and 83 (B.L. Paulson &amp; S.L. Paulson trans., Clarendon 1992): “Interpretation is an intellectual activity that accompanies the law-creating process as it moves from a higher level of the hierarchical structure to the lower level governed by this higher level ... even the judge creates law, even he is relatively independent in this capacity”; H. Kelsen, <emph type="i">Pure Theory of Law</emph> (M. Knight trans., The Lawbook Exchange 2009); H. Kelsen, <emph type="i">General Theory of Law and State</emph> p. 134 (A. Wedberg trans., Transaction 2009): “The judicial function is thus, like legislation, both creation and application of law”; H.L.A. Hart, <emph type="i">The Concept of Law</emph> pp. 272-275 (3rd ed., Oxford University 2012); H.L.A. Hart, <emph type="i">American Jurisprudence through English Eyes: The Nightmare and the Noble Dream</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Essays in Jurisprudence and Philosophy</emph> pp. 125-126 (Clarendon 1983), writing that “[t]he Nightmare is that this image of the judge, distinguishing him from the legislator, is an illusion, and the expectations which it excites are doomed to disappointment – on an extreme view, always, and on a moderate view, very frequently”, and that “what the courts were doing seems to the English lawyer, at first sight at any rate, particularly hard to justify in a democracy”. <emph type="i">See also</emph> T.R. Bustamante, <emph type="i">A Criação do Direito pela Jurisprudência: Notas sobre a Aplicação do Direito e a Epistemologia na Teoria Pura do Direito</emph>, in <emph type="i">Contra o Absoluto: Perspectivas Críticas, Políticas e Filosóficas da Obra de Hans Kelsen</emph> p. 423 (A.S.M.C. Matos e A.B. Santos Neto eds., Juruá 2012): “Even theories that aspire to go beyond the limits of the descriptivism in the pure theory of law, like the theoretical developments of legal argumentation by Robert Alexy, Aulis Aarnio, Aleksander Peczenik, Manuel Atienza and, in a sense, Neil MacCormick, do not move away from Kelsen’s explanation of the dynamic moment of law and the process of application of legal norms” [author’s translation]. Among tax scholars, Misabel Derzi has written an entire book on the law-making power of judges and its consequences to the ideals of the rule of law. <emph type="i">See</emph> M.A.M. Derzi, <emph type="i">Modificações Jurisprudenciais do Direito Tributário: Proteção da Confiança, Boa-Fé Objetiva e Irretroatividade como Limitações Constitucionais ao Poder Judicial de Tributar</emph> (Noeses 2009). Partially because of these observations, the idea of judicial review and the democratic legitimacy of constitutional courts are constantly under attack. <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., T. Bustamante, <emph type="i">The Ongoing Search for Legitimacy: Can a ‘Pragmatic yet Principled’ Deliberative Model Justify the Authority of Constitutional Courts?</emph>, 78 Mod. L. Rev. 2 (2015). For an overview, <emph type="i">see</emph> J. Waldron, <emph type="i">The Core of the Case against Judicial Review</emph>, in <emph type="i">Political Political Theory: Essays on Institutions</emph> p. 199 (Harvard University 2016), arguing that judicial review “is politically illegitimate, so far as democratic values are concerned: by privileging majority voting among a small number of unelected and unaccountable judges, it disenfranchises ordinary citizens and brushes aside cherished principles of representation and political equality in the ﬁnal resolution of issues about rights”.</p>
                  </footnote> This is so not merely in the sense that legal decisions translate “law in the books” into “law in action”, but mainly because the meanings of legal texts are themselves a product of interpretation.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_104" label="104.">
                     <p> I. Venzke, <emph type="i">How Interpretation Makes International Law: On Semantic Change and Normative Twists</emph> p. 4 (Oxford University 2012): “The meaning of norms is the product of legal practice. Practice itself has to bear the burden of completing the lawmaking process in concrete instances by interpreting the relevant texts. A norm’s meaning does not lie hidden in or behind the norm text itself but is a product of interpretation. The practice of interpretation then also accounts for the semantic change and legal developments. Interpretations may further provide new reference points for legal discourse and they structure the space for legal argument. The practice of interpretation shifts and generates legal normativity. If nothing else, this position fundamentally challenges the common narrative according to which international law owes its existence and normativity to the consent of its subjects”. </p>
                  </footnote> This makes the job of justifying the decisions of a supranational group of judges even more difficult,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_105" label="105.">
                     <p> In the specific context of international human rights law, it would be easier to argue that judicial review by a supranational court accords with democratic principles. For an attempt, <emph type="i">see </emph>A. Follesdal, <emph type="i">Why International Human Rights Judicial Review might be Democratically Legitimate</emph>, 52 Scandinavian Stud. L. 103 (2007); A. Follesdal, <emph type="i">Why the European Court of Human Rights might be Democratically Legitimate: A Modest Defense</emph>, 27 Nordisk Tidsskrift for Menneskerettigheter 289 (2009). And about the judicial protection of the rights of taxpayers, <emph type="i">see</emph> R.G. Antón, <emph type="i"><extxref target="wtj_2018_1_int_2">The Fragmentation of Taxpayers’ Rights in International Dispute Resolution Settings: Healing Anxieties through Judicial Dialogue</extxref></emph>, 10 World Tax J. 1 (2018), Journals IBFD.</p>
                  </footnote> especially given that, in practice, the ITO envisaged by Dietsch and Rixen would operate as a technical, purportedly apolitical, body, producing global norms through the application of economic theory. </p>
               <p>Although Dietsch and Rixen may view their institutional solution as a forum for negotiations, this is not entirely the case because states would not be allowed to challenge the two basic principles of international tax justice. The decision-making procedures would go as far as to “defi[ne] the rules in line with the membership principle and the fiscal policy constraint”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_106" label="106.">
                     <p> Dietsch &amp; Rixen, <emph type="i">Tax Competition and Global Background Justice</emph>, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>, at p. 167. </p>
                  </footnote> To be fair, they do consider the objection of an anonymous referee that their ITO “is another non-majoritarian institution which is provided with substantial enforcement powers but lacks democratic accountability and legitimacy”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_107" label="107.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 169.</p>
                  </footnote> But they insist on a consequentialist response that does not really solve the issue raised;<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_108" label="108.">
                     <p> Id., at pp. 169-170: “This is an important concern. Yet, we believe that the <emph type="i">status quo</emph>, with its hollowing out of effective fiscal sovereignty through tax competition ... is even more problematic in this respect. Although it <emph type="i">formally </emph>guarantees democratic accountability, <emph type="i">de facto </emph>this is not the case. Conversely, while an ITO may reduce the scope of fiscal policy issues for which there is direct democratic accountability, it would make sure that the latter can actually work effectively in this restricted realm”.</p>
                  </footnote> in the end, their proposal has to rely on a far-fetched comparative analysis with the status quo, which they take to be the worst-case scenario. </p>
               <p>More than disregarding the possibility of disagreement among countries on this particular matter,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_109" label="109.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See </emph>Ring, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_91">n. 91</xref>, at p. 574: “arguments regarding tax competition are not confined to an efficiency framework but extend beyond to encompass ideas of international political structure and global society. Some states resist efforts to change harmful tax practices on the grounds that these practices are valuable from their <emph type="i">sovereign </emph>perspective (even if potentially inefficient globally). Of course the states challenging tax competition consider certain competitive practices to be harmful from their sovereign perspective. Thus, there is a clash of sovereign positions, and an appeal to global efficiency provides no clear trump card”. </p>
                  </footnote> Dietsch and Rixen’s argument ultimately rests on their own assessment of the (un)desirability of tax competition. There is no need, in their view, to consult with each and every state first, or to give states the opportunity to express what they believe to be the best solution (or even to define the problems). Instead, Dietsch and Rixen imply that they already know what international tax justice requires.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_110" label="110.">
                     <p> This attitude amounts to a form of philosophical absolutism, whose classical followers, “the great metaphysicians, were in favor of political absolutism and against democracy”. Kelsen, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_91">n. 91</xref>, opposing political relativism and democracy to political absolutism and autocracy. <emph type="i">Accord </emph>R. Rorty, <emph type="i">An Ethics for Today: Finding Common Ground between Philosophy and Religion</emph> pp. 11-12 (Columbia University 2011), citing Pope Benedict XVI, who once wrote that “[r]elativism appears to be the philosophical foundation of democracy”, a stance taken by philosophers John Stuart Mill, John Dewey, and Jürgen Habermas. </p>
                  </footnote> Significantly, in the desire to spell out universal tax norms, Dietsch and Rixen overlook the likelihood that other countries’ cultures, histories, traditions, world views and relative socio-economic reputations, might provide completely different principles (or different interpretations of the same principles). This is a position criticized by Martti Koskenniemi: </p>
               <longquote>
                  <p>It follows that a person, group, or a State that does not share [those universal rational norms] is not only of another opinion (or preference) but has made a mistake about something that that person, group, or State should think rational for itself, too. Universalizability in theory leads automatically to expansion as practice. If my principle is valid because it is universal, then I not only may but perhaps must try to make others accept it as well. In any case, I can rest confident that I know what principles apply not only to me and my group but to any person or any group. If I engage in contacts with them, I need not face them as equals. I need not be open to their preferences because I already know that mine are universally valid, for me as well as for them, too. I may (or perhaps must) be kind towards and patient with them, but the object of my encounter can only be the transformation of the way they see the world, having them accept my principles, too (because they are not really “mine” but universally good).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_111" label="111.">
                        <p> M. Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">The Gentle Civilizer of Nations: The Rise and Fall of International Law 1870-1960</emph> p. 490 (Cambridge University 2004).</p>
                     </footnote>
                  </p>
               </longquote>
               <p>It is not necessary to search far to find disagreement on the principles of international taxation. Bamford’s critical essay on Dietsch and Rixen provides one good example.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_112" label="112.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See </emph>Bamford, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>.</p>
                  </footnote> Bamford challenges both of Dietsch and Rixen’s principles from a philosophical perspective and provides two alternatives: the principle of relationship and the principle of counter-incentive. With respect to the first, Bamford emphasizes that not only may legal persons be affiliated with more than one country, but also natural persons, and this leads him to conclude that a principle that focuses on relationships would be more appropriate. For him, multiple relationships should be measured on the basis of economic allegiance.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_113" label="113.">
                     <p> For individuals, Bamford considers possible criteria such as birth, parentage, citizenship, education, residence and location of earnings from labour and/or from investment. In the case of companies, since head of office and of incorporation can be easily manipulated, he agrees with Dietsch and Rixen that we should apply formulaic apportionment.</p>
                  </footnote> This is not an original criterion; rather, it is one of the core principles of the current ITR, which was established in the 1920-30s.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_114" label="114.">
                     <p> Economic allegiance was a criterion developed by the famous “four economics professors” that the League of Nations asked to elaborate a technical report on how to assign taxing rights among countries. These experts all came from developed countries: Italy, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom and the United States. <emph type="i">See generally </emph>H.D. Rosenbloom &amp; S.L. Langbein, <emph type="i">United States Tax Treaty Policy: An Overview</emph>, 19 Colum. J. Transnat’l L. 359 (1981); M.J. Graetz &amp; M.M. O’Hear, <emph type="i">The “Original Intent” of U.S. International Taxation</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Follow the Money: Essays on International Taxation</emph> (M.J. Graetz, Lillian Goldman Law Library 2016). For a critical analysis of their report, <emph type="i">see </emph>A. Christians, <emph type="i">BEPS and the Power to Tax</emph>, in <emph type="i">Tax Sovereignty in the BEPS Era</emph> (S.A. Rocha &amp; A. Christians eds., Wolters Kluwer 2017).</p>
                  </footnote> As for the second principle, Bamford proposes that, instead of putting a constraint on states’ fiscal policies, a “rewarding” system for high-tax countries should be introduced that ensures they get a larger bite of the global tax pie.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_115" label="115.">
                     <p> It is unclear what Bamford really means by the word “reward”. If what he has in mind is that high-tax countries would be able to tax exactly what they were supposed to in the absence of tax competition, then we are not talking about a reward system, but about a harmonized system aimed at neutralizing tax incentives from other countries. </p>
                  </footnote> 
               </p>
               <p>Bamford’s proposal is itself not without problems, being also subject to a range of criticisms. For instance, it can be argued that taking the world as it is, here and now, rewarding countries with higher taxes means rewarding rich countries. In a world with vast disparities of power and wealth across countries, eliminating tax competition without some form of compensation (like a global redistributive scheme or, less ambitiously, a better allocation of global tax revenues) would amount to an extremely regressive world tax regime,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_116" label="116.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See </emph>T. Dagan, <emph type="i">Just Harmonization</emph>, 42 U.B.C. L. Rev. 331, p. 361 (2010): “If political justice and redistribution within states is what we strive for, then – assuming tax competition drives tax rates to the bottom – countries do, indeed, need to coordinate their tax policies in order to prevent this race. Such harmonization, however, might benefit some (probably developed) countries while harming other (probably developing) countries. If, rather, cosmopolitan justice is what we seek, then a mechanism of cooperation far more elaborate than simple harmonization is required, whereby countries not only coordinate their tax rates and policies but also design a system for administering payments to welfare recipients”.</p>
                  </footnote> aggravating inequalities <emph type="i">among</emph> countries (i.e. “international/intercountry inequality”).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_117" label="117.">
                     <p> A.W. Cappelen, <emph type="i">National and International Distributive Justice in Bilateral Tax Treaties</emph>, 56 FinanzArchiv/Public Finance Analysis 3/4, pp. 424-425 (1999), observing that the “choice [of international tax principle] is, to some extent, a choice between national and international inequality”. For the distinction between international inequality (inequality among nations) and global inequality (inequality among individuals), <emph type="i">see</emph> B. Milanovic, <emph type="i">Worlds Apart: Measuring International and Global Inequality</emph> (Princeton University 2005).</p>
                  </footnote> It should be noted that this critique could also be applied to Dietsch and Rixen.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_118" label="118.">
                     <p> The same problem was identified in Thomas Piketty’s recent proposal to institute a global tax on capital. (<emph type="i">See </emph>Piketty, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_94">n. 94</xref>). M. Medeiros, <emph type="i">Piketty e Nós</emph>, Revista Piauí (May 2014), available at <url publish="y" target="http://piaui.folha.uol.com.br/materia/piketty-e-nos/">http://piaui.folha.uol.com.br/materia/piketty-e-nos/</url>:</p><longquote>
                        <p>[International] inequality, for example, is not considered in the book’s [Capital in the Twenty-First Century] debate. The French author does not give due attention to research that reveals inequality between countries, which is as important as inequality within countries. One way to understand this is to observe what happens with the Gini coefficient, an index commonly used to measure income inequality. The world’s Gini is higher than the Gini of any single country. Here, Piketty’s proposed solution to the problem of inequality fails. A country’s taxation retains taxes within it and therefore does nothing – at least directly – to reduce inequality between countries. By taxing the rich, the U.S. government would be taxing profits that have been obtained in other countries and brought to the United States. As a result, it would reduce inequality in their own country, but not in the world. [Author’s translation.]</p>
                     </longquote><p><emph type="i">Accord</emph> M. Stewart, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2018_04_int_13">Redistribution between Rich and Poor Countries</extxref></emph>, 72 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 4/5, p. 309 (2018), Journals IBFD: “simply ‘taxing’ such wealth (even if it were easy) is not going to be enough. We really do need to redistribute it, either through public goods or through social welfare systems. These proposals leave the redistributive task to governments of countries to achieve and do not address redistribution from rich to poor across countries”.</p></footnote> Moreover, Bamford’s counter-incentive principle could end up creating an incentive for all countries to increase their taxes, replacing a race to the bottom in tax rates with a race to the top in tax rates. Either way, it is hard to see how the fiscal self-determination, or de facto tax sovereignty, of states would not be undermined, since countries would continue to take decisions based on external forces. </p>
               <p>Be that as it may, Bamford’s proposal illustrates how it is possible to reasonably disagree on the basis of normative principles. Whatever the merits or demerits of his two principles, the point here is that if various experts cannot agree among themselves, it is not reasonable to expect all the world’s peoples to simply abide by any one proposal. To put in David Kennedy’s words, “[p]eople disagree about the most fundamental things” and “the challenges we face [will not] yield to technical expert consensus” because “they are political”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_119" label="119.">
                     <p> Kennedy, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_64">n. 64</xref>, at p. xi. <emph type="i">See also</emph> J. Waldron, <emph type="i">Law and Disagreement</emph> p. 1 (Clarendon 1999): “There are many of us, and we disagree about justice. That is, we not only disagree about the existence of God and the meaning of life; we disagree also about what count as fair terms of co-operation among people who disagree about the existence of God and the meaning of life. We disagree about what we owe to each other in the way of tolerance, forbearance, respect, co-operation, and mutual aid. Liberals disagree with conservatives; socialists disagree with market economists; the party of freedom disagrees with the party of community and both disagree with the party of equality; feminists disagree with those who want the government to stand up for ‘family values’; last-ditch defenders of the welfare state disagree with triumphant opponents of taxation; and pragmatists and utilitarians disagree with those who think the task of law is to vindicate the claims of order, retribution, and desert”.</p>
                  </footnote> Different minds will differ on what principles should regulate international tax relations and, as a consequence, how to allocate tax revenues across countries, sharing the fruits of economic globalization. </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_3_2_2" label="3.2.2.">
               <title>Will another international technical forum make a real difference?</title>
               <p>A new way of dealing with global tax issues has been recently suggested by Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_120" label="120.">
                     <p> 
                        <emph type="i">See</emph> Rosenbloom, Noked &amp; Helal, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_12">n. 12</xref>.</p>
                  </footnote> The authors begin by highlighting the shortcomings of the current international tax system, which is full of inconsistencies, inefficiencies and loopholes. Then, they proceed to evaluate a series of international forums for tax cooperation: the OECD, the G20, the United Nations, the European Union, the WTO, the IMF, the WB, as well as regional forums.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_121" label="121.">
                     <p> The Inter-American Center of Tax Administration (CIAT), the Commonwealth Association of Tax Administrators (CATA), the Pacific Association of Tax Administrators (PATA), the Intra-European Organization of Tax Administrations (IOTA), the General Assembly of the Meeting and Studies Center of Tax Administrations Directors (CREDAF), and the African Tax Administrations Forum (ATAF).</p>
                  </footnote> 
               </p>
               <p>Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal demonstrate that none of these existing international institutions “provide an adequate platform for countries with similar interests to engage in a true collaborative effort”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_122" label="122.">
                     <p> Rosenbloom, Noked &amp; Helal, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_12">n. 12</xref>, at p. 58.</p>
                  </footnote> One possible exception they consider is the Joint International Tax Shelter Information Centre (JITSIC), which is a forum that brings together a small number of countries concerned with tax avoidance and tax shelters.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_123" label="123.">
                     <p> Australia, Canada, China, Japan, South Korea, the United Kingdom and the United States.</p>
                  </footnote> However, since the scope of the JITSIC is too limited for engaging with tax policymaking, they reject it as a viable model.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_124" label="124.">
                     <p> Rosenbloom, Noked &amp; Helal, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_12">n. 12</xref>, at p. 75.</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>Their proposal consists in the creation of a novel international institution, but not exactly an ITO. Rather, they favour the establishment of an informal tax cooperation forum (TCF) modelled on what is known as a “like-minded group” (LMG). Stressing the importance of multilateralism, they argue informal forums could promote efforts with respect to: (i) multilateral tax treaties; (ii) formulary apportionment or other alternatives to transfer pricing; (iii) standardized anti-avoidance measures (e.g. CFC rules) and source and transfer pricing rules; (iv) tax arbitrage; (v) tax competition; (vi) harmonization of tax rates on capital income and of reporting rules; (vii) taxation of intellectual property; (viii) dispute resolution; and (ix) administrative cooperation.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_125" label="125.">
                     <p> Id., at pp. 82-83.</p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>A serious difficulty with this proposal is that it lacks the necessary formality that could guarantee meaningful change. By suggesting that these TCFs could operate on an informal basis, Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal may contribute to perpetuating the same technocratic networked governance structures that have long been associated with problems such as “technocratic elitism”, “distortion of national political processes”, “unrepresentative input into global political processes”, “the ineradicability of power”, and so forth.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_126" label="126.">
                     <p> A.-M. Slaughter, <emph type="i">A New World Order</emph> pp. 217-260 (Princeton University 2004).</p>
                  </footnote> This unwarranted faith in informality seems to stem from a particular short-sighted view of IR, usually attributed to the neoliberal tradition. When such IR theorists, also known as liberal institutionalists, talk about international regimes, they confine their analysis to governments’ attempts to overcome market failures, such as the inconsistencies, inefficiencies and loopholes emphasized by Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal. But in doing so, they pay inadequate attention to the dynamics of power struggles. Drawing on the neorealism in IR (identified by authors like Kenneth Waltz and Stephen Krasner), Diane Ring contends that power can shape the international tax game, since powerful states can determine (i) who can join the game, (ii) what the rules of game are (e.g. who can make the first move), and even (iii) the order of preferences of weaker players (the so-called “payoff matrix”).<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_127" label="127.">
                     <p> Ring, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_25">n. 25</xref>, at p. 101. </p>
                  </footnote> This analysis accurately captures an observation made by Horner in her 2001 article: “[t]he OECD likes to claim that it develops the ‘rules of the game’, but unfortunately not all players are at the table”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_128" label="128.">
                     <p> Horner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_73">n. 73</xref>, at p. 182. </p>
                  </footnote> Horner further noticed that “[i]f the OECD wants to be the facilitator of truly global rules of the game, it must find a way to put the developing world at the table with a real and meaningful voice”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_129" label="129.">
                     <p> Id., at p. 179. </p>
                  </footnote>
               </p>
               <p>Likewise, Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal do not take into consideration recent debates in democratic theory, regarding political institutional practices that extend beyond the nation state. This is the focus of <xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_4">section 4.</xref></p>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_4" label="4.">
         <title>International Tax Law between Legality and Legitimacy</title>
         <p>This section builds on the ideas of political and democratic theorists, as they apply to the world order. The goal is to situate international taxation within the legitimation requirements of procedural fairness, deliberation and participation, with the aim of constructing political decision-making capabilities of dialogue and communication in and beyond the state. First, this section addresses a possible solution: the argument that legalizing the world of tax – converting “tax governance” into “tax law” – could domesticate power and control arbitrariness. It then proceeds to explore the politics of global tax governance and a possible democratically centred model for tax law and policy, as an alternative for either a global tax regulator or a global tax court.</p>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_4_1" label="4.1.">
            <title>From international tax soft law to international tax hard law: Why legalization is not enough</title>
            <p>One claim that has been made is that world politics should be subjected to legalization.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_130" label="130.">
                  <p> J.L. Dunoff &amp; M.A. Pollack, <emph type="i">International Law and International Relations: Introducing an Interdisciplinary Dialogue</emph>, in <emph type="i">Interdisciplinary Perspectives on Law and International Relations: The State of the Art</emph> p. 3 (J.L. Dunoff &amp; M.A. Pollack eds., Cambridge University 2013): “By the early 2000s, political scientists in turn ‘rediscovered’ international law, a development marked most clearly by the publication of a special issue of <emph type="i">International Organization</emph>, the leading journal in the field, devoted to understanding the causes and consequences of the ‘legalization’ of international politics”. The articles in this special issue were republished in book form as J.L. Goldstein et al. eds., <emph type="i">Legalization and World Politics</emph> (The MIT 2001). </p>
               </footnote> The idea is that if a system of international hard (tax) law could be created in place of the current system of international soft (tax) law, the legitimacy issue would resolve itself.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_131" label="131.">
                  <p> This is the motivation behind the OECD’s so-called “multilateral instrument” or MLI (<emph type="i"><extxref target="tt_o2_02_eng_2016_tt__td1">Multilateral Convention to Implement Tax Treaty Related Measures to Prevent Base Erosion and Profit Shifting</extxref></emph> (7 June 2017), Treaties IBFD). <emph type="i">See </emph>Christians, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_4">n. 4</xref>, at p. 1602: “the multilateral codification function may be an exercise in creping harmonization as well as a means to gradually ossify other forms of OECD soft law into hard law. [...] It is, finally, the multilateral agreement on tax that the original experts of the League of Nations had so hoped for and worked toward”.</p>
               </footnote> However, the legalization of global (tax) governance alone is far from sufficient. The absence of a broader democratic scheme that ensures inclusiveness, accountability, transparency and responsiveness threatens to consolidate the privileged position of powerful nations and private groups. In the presence of a new institutional superstructure, these global actors would focus on validating and reasserting their existing influence and expertise.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_132" label="132.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>S. Picciotto, <emph type="i">Regulating Global Corporate Capitalism</emph> p. 468 (Cambridge University 2011). </p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>Besides, “[d]epending on the governance structure of the international cooperation arrangement or world tax body, developing countries might find themselves working to an agenda that mainly helps countries that are already leaders in transnational business”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_133" label="133.">
                  <p> Horner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_73">n. 73</xref>, at p. 183.</p>
               </footnote> On the one hand, “[i]t would be naïve to see ‘networked governance’ separately from interests, ideas and power relations”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_134" label="134.">
                  <p> Lesage, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_81">n. 81</xref>, at p. 288.</p>
               </footnote> On the other, “[i]t is clearly illusory to consider that law alone can provide adequate legitimacy for global governance”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_135" label="135.">
                  <p> Picciotto, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_132">n. 132</xref>, at p. 468.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>What emerges from the proposals by Dietsch and Rixen, as well as those by Bamford, is a legalistic, judge-centric system of international dispute settlement,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_136" label="136.">
                  <p> M.P. Cottrell &amp; D.M. Trubek, <emph type="i">Law as Problem Solving: Standards, Networks, Experimentation, and Deliberation in Global Space</emph>, 21 Transnat’l L. &amp; Contemp. Probs. 359, p. 361 (2012): “legalist approaches to international law emphasize command and control regulation in which courts and similar bodies that apply sanctions for non-compliance lay down and enforce relatively specific rules that define allowable behavior”. For a classical concept of legalization, <emph type="i">see</emph> K.W. Abbott et al., <emph type="i">The Concept of Legalization</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Legalization and World Politics</emph> p. 34 (The MIT 2001): “Highly legalized institutions are those in which rules are obligatory on parties through links to the established rules and principles of international law, in which rules are precise (or can be made precise through the exercise of delegated authority), and in which authority to interpret and apply the rules has been delegated to third parties acting under the constraint of rules”.<emph type="i"> See also </emph>K.W. Abbott &amp; D. Snidal, <emph type="i">Law, Legalization, and Politics: An Agenda for the Next Generation of IL/IR Scholars</emph>, in <emph type="i">Interdisciplinary Perspectives on Law and International Relations: The State of the Art</emph> p. 34 (J.L. Dunoff &amp; M.A. Pollack eds., Cambridge University 2013), distinguishing between “law” and “legalization”: “‘[l]aw’ refers to the legal system and the body of legal rules, procedures, discourses, and institutions existing at a point in time; ‘legalization’ refers to the process of adding to, changing, or subtracting from the body of law and the legal system over time”.</p>
               </footnote> according to which “nations would then face governance by a group of unelected, multinational judges striking down domestic laws on the basis of economic theory”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_137" label="137.">
                  <p> G.R. Shell, <emph type="i">Trade Legalism and International Relations Theory: An Analysis of the World Trade Organization</emph>, 44 Duke L. J. 829, p. 906 (1995).</p>
               </footnote> Dietsch and Rixen argue that in order for states to regain their de facto fiscal power, these same states would have to accept limitations on their de jure fiscal power imposed by the rulings of an ITO. But such a regime “is likely to promote cooperation by clarifying treaty norms <emph type="i">only</emph> if countries perceive the resulting interpretation of the norms to be legitimate” [emphasis added].<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_138" label="138.">
                  <p> R.A. Green, <emph type="i">Antilegalistic Approaches to Resolving Disputes between Governments: A Comparison of the International Tax and Trade Regime</emph>, 23 Yale J. Int’l L. 79, p. 133 (1998).</p>
               </footnote> As the 40-year-long tax controversy between the United States and the European Union over US export subsidizing through income tax exemptions demonstrates,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_139" label="139.">
                  <p> This long-lasting dispute was initiated under the old General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) system, by the time the European Union brought a case against the DISC regime enacted by US Congress. The drama continued after the establishment of the WTO, with respect to the Foreign Sales Corporation (FSC), Extraterritorial Income Exclusion (ETI), and Jobs Act regimes, all of which were considered in violation of WTO law. </p>
               </footnote> the trade-off between de jure and de facto sovereignty “may depend in part on satisfaction with the outcomes”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_140" label="140.">
                  <p> D. Ring, <emph type="i">What’s at Stake in the Sovereignty Debate: International Tax and the Nation-State</emph>, 49 Va. J. Int’l L. 155, p. 225 (2008).</p>
               </footnote> The reaction of US politicians, who harshly criticized these decisions for infringing on the sovereign power of the United States,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_141" label="141.">
                  <p> Id., at pp. 219-223. </p>
               </footnote> exposes the ongoing lack of legitimacy of the WTO model.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_142" label="142.">
                  <p> Brauner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_27">n. 27</xref>, at p. 316.</p>
               </footnote> For an international tax law regime to properly function, it has to be accepted and internalized by all of the parties affected. This requires not another body of legal experts, but instead mechanisms for open communication, experimentation, reflexivity and political contestation.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_4_2" label="4.2.">
            <title>What about the so-called “political”? The Repercussions of <emph type="i">Smith vs. Jones</emph></title>
            <p>The democratic deficit problem constantly surfaces when proposals focus exclusively on the outcomes and forget the processes of formation of political will. A comment made by an anonymous reviewer of this article illustrates this point. It was emphasized that, although biased towards OECD member countries (and perhaps even more towards multinational companies), the ITR should nevertheless be appreciated for having increased cross-border trade and investment in the post-World War II liberal order, bolstering peace and reducing conflict.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_143" label="143.">
                  <p> But<emph type="i"> see </emph>A.H. Rosenzweig, <emph type="i">Integrating Tax and Development Policy</emph>, JOTWELL (2013): “Originally, the policy behind tax treaties was to lower tax barriers to cross-border trade – as barriers dropped, trade increased, making everyone better off. What this theory did not take into account, however, was that this only worked for countries between which trade would flow. That is, countries with roughly similar economies. But what about small, capital poor countries? What would they get in return for signing a tax treaty with a wealthy country? The emerging consensus is: nothing”.</p>
               </footnote> The reasoning begs the question by trying to justify means with ends, concentrating solely on some sort of “output legitimacy”. Yet the very problem to be addressed – reflected in the quotation at the beginning of this article (“Who decides what and how to tax, and for whose benefit?”) – is precisely the lack of “input legitimacy” that exposes the antidemocratic nature of the current international tax order.</p>
            <p>This appears acute when the ITO envisaged by Dietsch, Rixen and Bamford is considered. Their proposal would effectively serve as an international court to resolve tax disputes on the basis of predefined principles. This approach disregards that the underlying problems of international taxation lie squarely on reaching a universal agreement on what norms should regulate international fiscal relations, given that any choice already presupposes a division of the global tax base.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_144" label="144.">
                  <p> M. Sato &amp; R.M. Bird, <emph type="i">International Aspects of the Taxation of Corporations and Shareholders</emph>, 22 IMF Staff Papers 384 (1975); Avi-Yonah, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_52">n. 52</xref>, p. 1303; Cappelen, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_117">n. 117</xref>; T. Dagan, <emph type="i">The Costs of International Tax Cooperation</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Welfare State, Globalization, and International Law</emph> (E. Benvenisti &amp; G. Nolte eds., Springer 2004); A. Christians, <emph type="i">How Nations Share</emph>, 87 Ind. L. J. 1407 (2012); I. Benshalom, <emph type="i">How to Redistribute? A Critical Examination of Mechanisms to Promote Global Wealth Redistribution</emph>, 64 U. Toronto L. J. 317 (2014); A.H. Rosenzweig, <emph type="i">Defining a Country’s “Fair Share” of Taxes</emph>, 42 Fla. St. U. L. Rev. 373 (2015); I. Grinberg, <emph type="i">Does FATCA Teach Broader Lessons about International Tax Multilateralism?</emph>, in <emph type="i">Global Tax Governance: What Is Wrong with It and How to Fix It</emph> p. 8 (P. Dietsch &amp; T. Rixen eds., ECPR 2016).</p>
               </footnote> Dietsch, Rixen and Bamford do not even specify the framework of decision-making processes under which their ITO would operate at the supranational level. When put into practice, their well-intentioned idea of building a just tax order runs the risk of simply creating yet another bureaucratic global apparatus that will exert a kind of post-democratic political authority.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_145" label="145.">
                  <p> This problem is also at the root of the legitimacy crisis of the European Union. <emph type="i">See generally</emph> Z. Bauman, <emph type="i">Europe: An Unfinished Adventure</emph> (Polity 2004); J. Habermas, <emph type="i">The Crisis of the European Union: A Response</emph> (C. Cronin trans., Polity 2012); U. Beck, <emph type="i">German Europe</emph> (R. Livingstone trans., Polity 2013); A. Giddens, <emph type="i">Turbulent and Mighty Continent: What Future for Europe?</emph> (Polity 2014); W. Streeck, <emph type="i">Buying Time: The Delayed Crisis of Democratic Capitalism </emph>(P. Camiller trans., Verso 2014); C. Offe, <emph type="i">Europe Entrapped</emph> (C. Cronin trans., Polity 2015). <emph type="i">See also </emph>H. Brunkhorst, <emph type="i">The Legitimation Crisis of the European Union</emph>, 13 Constellations 165 (2006); T. Pogge, <emph type="i">Politics as Usual: What Lies Behind the Pro-Poor Rhetoric</emph> p. 183 et seq. (Polity 2010).</p>
               </footnote> Such a purportedly pragmatic method, therefore, fails to engage with critical questions about how and why the form of supranational decision-making they envisage would accord with democratic principles. </p>
            <p>The flaw underlying all international tax coordination proposals to date may be traced to what Fraser calls the “Keynesian-Westphalian frame”, a phrase that “is meant to signal the national-territorial underpinnings of justice disputes in the heyday of the postwar democratic welfare state, roughly 1945 through the 1970s”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_146" label="146.">
                  <p> Fraser, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13">n. 13</xref>, at p. 11. For the embracement of Fraser’s theory of global justice by a TWAIL-er (Third World Approaches to International Law scholar), <emph type="i">see </emph>B.S. Chimni, <emph type="i">A Just World Under Law: A View from the South</emph>, 22 Am. U. Int’l L. Rev. 199 (2007).</p>
               </footnote> The problem with this framing is that it no longer holds for a globalizing world, where peoples’ lives are more and more impacted by decisions taken outside the territorial state. Now that countries’ economies are more interdependent, and unilateral redistributive policies in one country are much harder to achieve,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_147" label="147.">
                  <p> J. Habermas, <emph type="i">The Postnational Constellation and the Future of Democracy</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Postnational Constellation: Political Essays</emph> p. 79 (M. Pensky trans., The MIT 2001). <emph type="i">See also </emph>T. Dagan, <emph type="i">The Global Market for Tax and Legal Rules</emph>, 21 Flo. Tax Rev. 148 (2017).</p>
               </footnote> the very idea of fiscal self-determination might lose some of its appeal. Most importantly, as justice claims transcend the national level, political principles must take on a transnational form, in order to make democratic governance possible. </p>
            <p>Surprisingly, even authors trained in political philosophy neglect this political dimension of justice.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_148" label="148.">
                  <p> As Fraser explains, this flaw is evident among liberals and communitarians, with some exceptions (e.g. Michael Walzer, Iris Marion Young, Amartya Sen and Seyla Benhabib). By contrast, deliberative democrats (Jürgen Habermas, Amy Gutmann and Dennis Thompson), agonistic democrats (William Connolly, Bonnie Honig, Chantal Mouffe and James Tully), and republicans (Quentin Skinner and Philip Pettit) have all sought to develop powerful theories of the political, but arguably without making an explicit connection with the idea of justice. According to Fraser, who admits she incurred the same mistake in the past, “an adequate theory of justice for our time must be three-dimensional”. For this reason, she argues for a theory of <emph type="i">post-Westphalian democratic justice</emph> that fully integrates struggles against maldistribution (the economic dimension), misrecognition (the cultural dimension) and misrepresentation (the political dimension). Fraser, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13">n. 13</xref>, at pp. 192-193, 194 n. 9, 200 and 206.</p>
               </footnote> Like many others before them, the theories of Dietsch and Rixen, and Bamford say nothing about <emph type="i">the political</emph>.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_149" label="149.">
                  <p> Reworking Carl Schmitt’s classical conceptualization of the political, Chantal Mouffe defends the institutionalization of a form of <emph type="i">antagonism between 
                     adversaries</emph> (“agonism”), in order to prevent that others are seen as enemies to be destroyed. She also criticizes rationalist models of democracy – or what she calls the post-political vision of politics – for denying the ineradicability of social conflicts and negativity. <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., C. Mouffe, <emph type="i">The Return of the Political</emph> (Verso 1993); C. Mouffe, <emph type="i">On the Political </emph>(Routledge 2006). <emph type="i">See also </emph>C. Mouffe, <emph type="i">Carl Schmitt’s Warning on the Dangers of a Unipolar World</emph>, in <emph type="i">The International Political Thought of Carl Schmitt: Terror, Liberal War and the Crisis of Global Order</emph> pp. 152-153 (L. Odysseos &amp; F. Petito eds., Routledge 2007): “The central problem that our current unipolar world is facing is that it is impossible for antagonisms to find legitimate forms of expression. It is no wonder, then, that those antagonisms, when they emerge, take extreme forms, putting into question the very structure of the existing international order. It is, in my view, the lack of political channels for challenging the hegemony of the neo-liberal model of globalization which is at the origin of the proliferation of discourses and practices of radical negation of the established order. In order to create channels for the legitimate expression of dissent we need to envisage a pluralistic world order constructed around a certain number of great spaces and genuine cultural poles”.</p>
               </footnote> When it comes to justice, the dimension of the political is the one that “tells us who is included in, and who excluded from, the circle of those entitled to a just distribution and reciprocal recognition”, and that “tells us not only who can make claims for redistribution and recognition, but also how such claims are to be mooted and adjudicated”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_150" label="150.">
                  <p> Fraser, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13">n. 13</xref>, at p. 195. </p>
               </footnote> Interestingly, the political dimension of representation addresses one of the most important questions about global governance: “If we wanted to do something about poverty or the environment – if we wanted to complain or protest or simply participate – to whom should we address ourselves?”<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_151" label="151.">
                  <p> Kennedy, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_63">n. 63</xref>, at p. 38.</p>
               </footnote> Resembling the widely recognized democratic principle in tax law of “no taxation without representation”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_152" label="152.">
                  <p> Note how the process of creeping fiscal harmonization carried out at the European Union has been criticized as a form of “European taxation without European representation”. Both the efforts undertaken by European governments (i.e. by members of the executive branch) and the “negative fiscal harmonization” resulting from the judgments of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) lack democratic legitimacy, because such intergovernmental and bureaucratic structures leave Member States and taxpayers underrepresented. J.C. Nabais, <emph type="i">A Soberania Fiscal no Actual Quadro de Internacionalização, Integração e Globalização Económicas</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Por um Estado Fiscal Suportável vol. 1: Estudos de Direito Fiscal</emph> p. 199 (Almedina 2005); J.C. Nabais, <emph type="i">A Soberania Fiscal no Actual Quadro da Integração Europeia</emph>, in <emph type="i">Por um Estado Fiscal Suportável vol. 2: Estudos de Direito Fiscal</emph> p. 29 (Almedina 2008).</p>
               </footnote> Fraser proclaims: “no redistribution or recognition without representation”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_153" label="153.">
                  <p> Fraser, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_13">n. 13</xref>, at p. 189.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>By relegating the political to the margin, theorists neglect deep-seated conflicts of interest and power struggles that are so dominant in the international scene.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_154" label="154.">
                  <p> Dean, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_32">n. 32</xref>, at p. 938: “The study of international tax is the study of conflicts”; O.A. Batista Jr., <emph type="i">Por Que a “Guerra Fiscal”? Os Desafios do Estado na Modernidade Líquida</emph> [<emph type="i">Why the “Fiscal War”? The Challenges of the State in the Liquid Modernity</emph>], 102 RBEP 305 (2011), arguing that states are always going to “war”, if not militarily, through their economic and fiscal systems; A. Christians, <emph type="i">Putting the Reign Back in Sovereign</emph>, 40 Pepp. L. Rev. (2013): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>Every nation-state in the world is both a participant and a potential victim in a global game of tax competition that erodes and undermines comprehensive income taxation wherever it is attempted. Each nation must safeguard its tax base against the aggressive maneuvering of its taxpayers, aided in their quest by too-easily manipulated rules and the complicity of foreign intermediaries – be they public or private – that stand to gain by being a mercenary in this global game. At the same time, each nation benefits itself by embracing mercenary behavior against other nations in order to capture as much global capital as possible, even if such action deprives other nations of revenue. [...] One way of looking at the post-Westphalian world is as a society of nations, divided along territorial lines, which are in direct competition with each other for the world's resources but enlightened enough to work with each other to prevent total war. In such a world, nations bind themselves and one another to the mast in international agreements with the intention of preventing the unwanted scenario of total destruction, but then engage in everyday acts of sabotage against these binds in order to advance their own interests at the expense of others. In taxation, the tendency toward this “agree in form, defect in practice” behavior is manifested in the means by which states create and manipulate for their own benefit an evolving set of international standards and norms (sometimes but not always of their own making) around a global flow of information about economic resources and their owners. </p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>Outside the tax field, <emph type="i">see </emph>R. Gilpin, <emph type="i">War and Change in World Politics</emph> 7 (Cambridge University 1981): “International relations continue to be a recurring struggle for wealth and power among independent actors in a state of anarchy”; J.J. Mearsheimer, <emph type="i">The Tragedy of Great Power Politics</emph> (W. W. Norton &amp; Company 2001): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>States employ a variety of means – economic, diplomatic, and military – to shift the balance of power in their favor, even if doing so makes other states suspicious or even hostile. Because one state’s gain in power is another state’s loss, great powers tend to have a zero-sum mentality when dealing with each other. The trick, of course, is to be the winner in this competition and to dominate the other states in the system. Thus, the claim that states maximize relative power is tantamount to arguing that states are disposed to think offensively toward other states, even though their ultimate motive is simply to survive. In short, great powers have aggressive intentions.</p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>José Luís Fiori, <emph type="i">Preface to Global Power</emph>, 2 Pers. World Rev. 125, p. 134 (2010): “For us, however, the real starting point of the ‘modern world system’ is embedded in the ‘national Economy-States’ ‘invented’ by Europeans and that became ‘power and wealth-accumulating machines’, endowed with a bigger ‘expansive compulsion’ than that of the first power and capitals established in Europe during the ‘long thirteenth century’”; R.D. Blackwill &amp; J.M. Harris, <emph type="i">War by Other Means: Geoeconomics and Statecraft </emph>(The Belknap Press of Harvard University 2016), expanding on the concept of geoeconomics, as the use of economic tools to advance geopolitical and foreign policy goals. </p>
               </footnote> Under the conditions of multiplicity of interests and values, trying to develop top-down principles that heavily depend on universally accepted outcomes, and then applying them to the entire world – as Rixen, Dietsch and Bamford attempt to do – is, to say the least, a daunting task.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_155" label="155.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>H. Patomäki, <emph type="i">Global Justice: A Democratic Perspective</emph>, in <emph type="i">Globalization and the Global Politics of Justice</emph> (B.K. Gills ed., Routledge 2008), maintaining that, in the face of a variety of competing conceptions of justice at the global stage, the quest should turn to the democratization of global governance systems; A. Sen, <emph type="i">The Idea of Justice </emph>p. 410 (The Belknap Press of Harvard University 2009), advocating that the recognition of a plurality of reasons for justice recommends a reach of global democracy, and that “[t]he challenge today is the strengthening of this already functioning participatory process, on which the pursuit of global justice will to a great extent depend”. <emph type="i">See also </emph>J.S. Dryzek, <emph type="i">The Deliberative Democrat’s Idea of Justice</emph>, 12 Eur. J. Polit. Theory 329 (2013), reviewing Sen’s book, and concluding that “[d]emocracy does not guarantee justice, but in a world of plural justice claims democracy is necessary to the pursuit of justice”; L. Valentini, <emph type="i">Justice, Disagreement and Democracy</emph>, 1 B. J. Pol. S. (2012), claiming that, in the presence of “thick reasonable disagreement”, democracy has intrinsic value, as a necessary demand of justice.</p>
               </footnote> Once it is taken into account that the world is pluralist and divided, it becomes clear how troubling it is to search for universalistic, all-encompassing solutions.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_156" label="156.">
                  <p> D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">One, Two, Three, Many Legal Orders: Legal Pluralism and the Cosmopolitan Dream</emph> 31 N.Y.U. Rev L &amp; Soc. Change 641, p. 658 (2007): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>Our global political world remains decentralized and horizontal. There is no one “international community”. The phrase refers to the particular elite who are the audience for the global media. We must recognize the idea that they share a “consensus” view of global political or ethical matters – or that their views condense the attitudes of humanity – as a fantasy. It may often be a desirable fantasy, and we may often want to encourage it, but is a fantasy. And it can be a dangerous fantasy. It can encourage us to think there is, in fact, an “international community” ready to back up pronouncements made in its name. It can encourage political elites to start projects and launch interventions, for which there will be no follow-up. It can suggest that those who disagree with these elites – and many do – are somehow outside the circuit of “civilization”. It can lead us to imagine that we know what justice is, always and everywhere. But, of course, we do not. Justice is not like that. It needs to be made anew in each time and in each place.</p>
                  </longquote>
               </footnote> The result is a major challenge to proposals such as those put forward by Dietsch, Rixen and Bamford. </p>
            <p>In the first place, these theories are vulnerable to the claim that they do not accommodate deep diversity among countries, including the likelihood of disagreement on whether the status quo is better or worse than in a world free of tax competition. Some developing countries could readily complain, for example, that this new world order would make it extremely hard for them to attract investments. Since tax incentives would be off the table, and assuming that these nations might not have a business-friendly environment due to poor infrastructure, they might be left with no alternative other than try to make up for their lack of economic advantage by using arguably more harmful regulatory competitive strategies, such as relaxing (even more) labour and environmental legislations.</p>
            <p>Countries disagree on what global solutions are actually needed and how they should be implemented, as in the obvious case of what should be the appropriate criteria for dividing the global tax base. In other words, Dietsch, Rixen and Bamford seem to disregard what John Rawls, in his mature work, came to dub “the fact of pluralism” – the diversity of comprehensive doctrines<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_157" label="157.">
                  <p> This is one of the main reasons that led him to reformulate his theory of justice, so that it could make room for reasonable disagreement. Rawls,<emph type="i"> supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_88">n. 88</xref>: “The fact of a plurality of reasonable but incompatible comprehensive doctrines – the fact of reasonable pluralism – shows that, as used in <emph type="i">Theory</emph> the idea of a well-ordered society of justice as fairness is unrealistic”.</p>
               </footnote> – or what Jürgen Habermas prefers to call “competing worldviews”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_158" label="158.">
                  <p> J. Habermas, <emph type="i">Between Facts and Norms: Contributions to a Discourse Theory of Law and Democracy</emph> pp. 60-61 (W. Rehg trans., 1996). </p>
               </footnote> which are much more intensified and persistent on the global stage. Indeed, being confronted with the pluralist character of today’s societies, these two renowned philosophers felt they had no other choice but to redirect their respective theories towards what came to be known as a “procedural turn” in political theory.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_159" label="159.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>J. Rawls, <emph type="i">The Idea of Public Reason Revisited</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The Law of Peoples: with “The Idea of Public Reason Revisited”</emph> (Harvard University 1999); J. Habermas, <emph type="i">Paradigms of Law</emph>, in<emph type="i"> Habermas on Law and Democracy: Critical Exchanges</emph> (M. Rosenfeld &amp; A. Arato eds., University of California 1998). On the Habermas-Rawls political dispute on how to address de facto pluralism of world views within the boundaries of the democratic constitutional state, <emph type="i">see </emph>J.G. Finlayson &amp; F. Freyenhagen eds., <emph type="i">Habermas and Rawls: Disputing the Political</emph> (Routledge 2011).</p>
               </footnote> Moreover, in the case of Rawls, coming to realize that some of the assumptions he had made in his acclaimed theory of justice as fairness were implausible eventually led him to a “political turn”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_160" label="160.">
                  <p> For the reasons why Rawls had to make this turn, <emph type="i">see </emph>P. Weithman, <emph type="i">Why Political Liberalism? On John Rawls’s Political Turn</emph> (Oxford University 2010).</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>In the second place, and probably most troubling for Dietsch, Rixen and Bamford, is the fact that their theories invite the heavy criticism that they perpetuate imperialistic forms of domination, oppression and injustice – which has been referred to as “informal (or postcolonial) imperialism”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_161" label="161.">
                  <p> J. Tully, <emph type="i">Public Philosophy in a New Key vol. 2: Imperialism and Civic Freedom</emph> pp. 134-135 (Cambridge University 2008): </p>
                  <longquote>
                     <p>Informal imperialism consists in, firstly, imposing a structure of domestic public law and political institutions, or “structurally adjusting” an existing constitutional order, that opens the resources, labour and markets of the imperialised country to free trade dominated by the great powers; and, secondly, subjecting this legal and political order in turn to regimes of public and private international laws, again constructed and dominated by the great powers. </p>
                  </longquote>
                  <p>In his critical reconstruction of how international law has been historically used to “civilize” the world, Koskenniemi refers to two forms of imperialism, rational and cynical, concluding that: “[r]ational imperialism turned out to be a façade for cynical imperialism”. Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_111">n. 111</xref>, at pp. 491-492 and 500. <emph type="i">See also </emph>A. Anghie, <emph type="i">Imperialism, Sovereignty and the Making of International Law</emph> (Cambridge University 2004), providing an alternative historical theory of international law and sovereignty based on the idea of “civilizing missions”.</p>
               </footnote> Weak countries would see a new global project to curb tax competition as a reiteration of the OECD’s initiative on “harmful” tax practices: an attempt to deprive them of one of their few sources of power, leaving them at the mercy of more powerful states. Once again, citing Horner: </p>
            <longquote>
               <p>Without a meaningful voice in such a forum, without basic conditions [...], developing countries may find that a global tax arrangement holds little interest and poses some dangers.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_162" label="162.">
                     <p> Horner, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_73">n. 73</xref>, at p. 187.</p>
                  </footnote> 
               </p>
            </longquote>
            <p>A realistic analysis must take seriously, and engage with, the problem of international struggles for power and wealth. Such an analysis would show that merely ending tax competition is not a satisfactory solution to global challenges, even if any such end could be achieved in practice, a doubtful proposition in any case.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_163" label="163.">
                  <p> Focusing on formal legal change without looking at how power and influence shape the way law is implemented in practice is an approach that is almost certainly doomed to fail. In Brazil, for example, state tax subsidies are constitutionally prohibited, unless there is an agreement among all 27 federal units. But that has not been able to stop states from engaging in harmful tax competition via confidential agreements among taxpayers and government officials. As long as governments can issue private rulings to specific parties, hiding tax breaks from public view, a “law on the books” approach will never be able to unearth them. At the international level, the <emph type="i">Lux Leaks</emph> case is a clear example of how, in the absence of effective accountability, transparency and democratic control, tax competition will never come to an end; it will only shift places. <emph type="i">See </emph>A. Christians, <emph type="i">Lux Leaks: Revealing the Law, One Plain Brown Envelope at a Time</emph>, Intl. Tax Notes (2014). </p>
               </footnote> Unless an articulated “international tax consensus” is the result of some sort of political-democratic method that includes subjects of the principles of fiscal justice – all states and their citizens – as co-authors,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_164" label="164.">
                  <p> I.M. Young, <emph type="i">Inclusion and Democracy</emph> pp. 5-6 (Oxford University 2000): “The normative legitimacy of a democratic decision depends on the degree to which those affected by it have been included in the decision-making processes and have had the opportunity to influence the outcomes”.</p>
               </footnote> it can be nothing more than an instrument of control imposed by the most powerful players – a “globalization from above” or “hegemonic globalization”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_165" label="165.">
                  <p> On these concepts, <emph type="i">see </emph>R.A. Falk, <emph type="i">Predatory Globalization: A Critique</emph> ch. 8 (Polity 1999): “Resisting ‘Globalization-from-Above’ through ‘Globalization-from-Below’”; P. Evans, <emph type="i">Fighting Marginalization with Transnational Networks: Counter-Hegemonic Globalization</emph>, 29 Contemp. Socio. 230 (2001), calling for a counterhegemonic globalization movement; P. Evans, <emph type="i">Counterhegemonic Globalization: Transnational Social Movements in the Contemporary Global Political Economy</emph>, in <emph type="i">The Handbook of Political Sociology: States, Civil Societies, and Globalization</emph> (T. Janoski et al. eds., Cambridge University 2005), analysing countermovements in contemporary world politics; B. Rajagopal, <emph type="i">International Law from Below: Development, Social Movements and Third World Resistance</emph> pp. 295-296 (Cambridge University 2003), defending an international legal theory based on “histories from below”, in order to “transform international law from an international law of domination to one of resistance in the aid of marginalized communities and peoples”; H.W. Afonso &amp; J.Q. de Magalhães, <emph type="i">Para Contar as Outras Estórias: Direito Internacional e Resistência Contra-Hegemônica no Terceiro Mundo </emph>[<emph type="i">Telling Other Stories: International Law and Counter-Hegemonic Resistance in the Third World</emph>], 29 Rev. Fac. Dir. Sul de Minas 155 (2013); G.W. Anderson, <emph type="i">Societal Constitutionalism, Social Movements, and Constitutionalism from Below</emph>, 20 Ind. J. Global Legal Stud. 881 (2013), incorporating transnational social movements within theories of constitutionalism beyond the state. <emph type="i">See also </emph>P. Bond, <emph type="i">Top Down or Bottom Up? A Reply</emph>, in <emph type="i">Debating Globalization </emph>(Held et al., Polity 2005), criticizing David Held’s cosmopolitan project for not being radical enough; B. Barber, <emph type="i">Global Governance from Below</emph>, in <emph type="i">Debating Globalization </emph>p. 103 (Held et al., Polity 2005): “The challenge today ... is to create the foundations for global governance from below even as governments and international organizations face the challenge of giving teeth to their common covenants”. <emph type="i">See generally </emph>B.S. Santos &amp; C.A. Rodríguez-Garavito eds., <emph type="i">Law and Globalization from Below: Towards a Cosmopolitan Legality</emph> (Cambridge University 2005).</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>Instead of yet again searching for a priori, ostensibly apolitical and rational principles of international taxation and then trying to construct an overarching coercive legal structure to achieve them, one should start from the bottom-up, thinking about how to include all those affected by the collective decision-making. Another intellectual strategy emanating from the Global North, no matter how elegant, therefore does not resolve the problem of the continuous exclusion of historically marginalized countries from initial regime formation. A legitimate ITR requires the improvement of discursive practices of decision-making at all levels of the globe (from the local to the global) – a political project that must include institutional choices of who should tax, where and what.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_166" label="166.">
                  <p> This question was posed by Richard Musgrave in a 1983 piece while dealing with interjurisdictional tax rules between subunits within a federation or confederation. <emph type="i">See </emph>R.A. Musgrave, <emph type="i">Public Finance in a Democratic Society vol. 3: The Foundations of Taxation and Expenditure</emph> (2000).</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>To achieve this kind of inclusion requires directing attention towards advancing mechanisms of participation and dialogue beyond the nation state, pushing further on for a comprehensive democratization of global tax governance. It is crucial to embrace basic legitimacy principles, such as the ideas of “global deliberative equality”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_167" label="167.">
                  <p> Slaughter, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_126">n. 126</xref>, at pp. 245-247.</p>
               </footnote> and “participatory parity”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_168" label="168.">
                  <p> This norm was introduced for the first time by Fraser, in her critique of Habermas’ conception of the public sphere. There, she asserted that, although full parity of participation within a polity is not always possible, we should still try to come as close as possible to this aspirational ideal by asking ourselves what institutional arrangements could narrow the gap between dominant and subordinate groups. N. Fraser, <emph type="i">Justice Interruptus: Critical Reflections on the “Postsocialist” Condition</emph> pp. 80-81 (Routledge 1997). At the international level, this notion is recast to focus on “the patterning of the broader space within which bounded polities are embedded and, so, to the question of who is included, and who excluded, from the circle of those entitled to participate within them”, and to address situations “when the partitioning of political spaces blocks some who are poor or despised from challenging the forces that oppress them”. N. Fraser, K. Nash &amp; V. Bell, <emph type="i">The Politics of Framing: An Interview with Nancy Fraser by Kate Nash and Vikki Bell</emph>, in <emph type="i">Scales of Justice: Reimagining Political Space in a Globalizing World</emph> pp. 142 and 147 (N. Fraser, Columbia University 2009).</p>
               </footnote> in view of creating more democratic and egalitarian global institutions. Only when states and their citizens acquire equally effective voices, having the opportunity to defend their specific fiscal interests and needs on an equal footing, while taking due account of (and also challenging) the perspectives of others, can the process of deciding global fiscal matters, and producing cosmopolitan tax norms, be deemed politically legitimate.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_169" label="169.">
                  <p> In a sense, this reasoning follows what Seyla Benhabib calls “democratic iterations”, i.e. a jurisgenerative politics of interpretation, argumentation, contestation, revision, resignification and rejection that should take place at various levels of the globe. As a practical matter, such an approach seeks to “reconcile cosmopolitanism with the unique legal, historical, and cultural traditions and memories of a people”. S. Benhabib, <emph type="i">Democratic Iterations: The Local, the National, and the Global</emph>, in <emph type="i">Another Cosmopolitanism</emph> p. 70 (R. Post ed., Oxford University 2006). It is also inspired by Jürgen Habermas’s democratic principle, which says: “only those statutes may claim legitimacy than can meet with the assent (<emph type="i">Zustimmung</emph>) of all citizens in a discursive process of legislation that in turn has been legally constituted”. <emph type="i">See </emph>Habermas, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_157">n. 157</xref>, at p. 110. Applying a Habermasian perspective to international tax law, Cees Peters concludes: “[t]here is no fixed idea about ‘fairness’ in international taxation and it is up to us mortals to define what is acceptable and what is not. [...] This should be a continuous and never-ending dialogue that is based on the recognition that taxpayers and states (and other players) are part of the international society as a whole. Only in this way it is possible to guarantee its legitimacy in the longer run”. Peters, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_3">n. 3</xref>, at p. 391.</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_4_3" label="4.3.">
            <title>Beyond technocracy and hegemony: For a pluralist and multipolar international tax order</title>
            <p>Given the implausibility of the models proposed so far, and concluding that all the above-mentioned solutions are, in some way or another, at odds with the proceeds of political influence necessary to validate supranational norms and institutions, it is time to return to the question posed by Tanzi 19 years ago: is there really a need for an ITO? </p>
            <p>The prospects of building an effective supranational tax institution with universal membership, meaning one that is really able to guarantee full inclusiveness and broad participation to all countries at once, do not seem very bright. An ITO would, at best, be part of the same international framework under the United Nations, an organization that has repeatedly failed to take action on behalf of poor countries, as in the case of promoting a more equitable ITR. Therefore, a comprehensive reform would be a vital first step.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_170" label="170.">
                  <p> But<emph type="i"> see </emph>Mouffe, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_149">n. 149</xref>, at p. 100: “as Danilo Zolo has convincingly argued, given the enormous disparity of power among its members, it is completely unrealistic to believe in the possibility of reforming the United Nations in order simultaneously to strengthen them and to make them more democratic”; M. Koskenniemi, <emph type="i">Book Review: “Globalization and Sovereignty: Rethinking Legality, Legitimacy and Constitutionalism”, by Jean L. Cohen</emph>, 11 Int’l J. Const. L. 818, p. 821 (2013), stating that “[t]he time of UN reform certainly is [past], and perhaps the same applies to the use of the European Union as a ‘model’ for something”.</p>
               </footnote> This is not impossible, but even so, creating another techno-bureaucratic supranational body with enforcement powers will not resolve the political legitimacy deficit of global tax governance; on the contrary, it might aggravate it. Marginalized countries do not need another technical forum to make progress towards a more just ITR, and they should not have to wait for a major UN reform.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_171" label="171.">
                  <p> Lesage, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_81">n. 81</xref>, at p. 289: “the existence of an ITO is not a guarantee for developing countries to bring about a ‘new taxation order’; they will need counterparts that share their agenda. Otherwise, the ITO could influence the debate only in its function as an alternative epistemic community and at best generate change at a very low pace. Therefore, developing countries interested in an alternative tax agenda should not concentrate too much on the formal universal level”.</p>
               </footnote> To advance their cause, these countries need better opportunities for political articulation at different levels and in different regions, even outside the UN scope.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_172" label="172.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 290.</p>
               </footnote> This could contribute to the emergence of other epistemic communities “that counter[ ] the marginalization of alternative views on national and international taxation”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_173" label="173.">
                  <p> Id., at p. 293.</p>
               </footnote> 
            </p>
            <p>To some extent, the LMG approach elected by Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal seems more appealing than all the competing proposals examined herein. Instead of ignoring the different fiscal interests at play – i.e. the heterogeneity of the tax world – the LMG approach embraces this plurality. However, giving in too quickly to the idea of informal regimes, the exponents do not address the issue of power and the political and distributional dimensions of international conflicts over taxation. As such, their model would only account for technical forums for the exchange of expertise among those countries that already have it. </p>
            <p>No real space for political resistance, deliberation or empowerment is encouraged within Rosenbloom, Noked and Helal’s proposal. Yet this is precisely what is needed: to pursue the establishment of strong political multilateral forums at both regional and global levels, so as to foster democratic contestation, deliberation and power sharing.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_174" label="174.">
                  <p> Such coalitions are not that uncommon, even in the area of international taxation, as exemplified by the International Trade and Investment Organization (ITIO): “a somewhat misleading name for a forum of OFCs in the Caribbean and the Pacific, created in 2001 to defend their interests in reaction to the OECD initiative on harmful tax competition”. Lesage, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_81">n. 81</xref>, at p. 292. A more recent example of institutions based upon a coalition of developing countries is the BRICs. For an initial evaluation of its role in shaping international tax, <emph type="i">see </emph>Y. Brauner &amp; P. Pistone eds., <emph type="i"><extxref target="bric_head">BRICS and the Emergence of International Tax Coordination</extxref></emph> (IBFD 2015).</p>
               </footnote> Contrary to celebrating the tendency observed among BRICs countries of convergence to OECD tax standards, non-members should be encouraged to form change-seeking coalitions that can, in turn, challenge OECD supremacy and break the status quo.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_175" label="175.">
                  <p> Dries Lesage has pointed out to me that global civil society actors might play an important role in this regard. For important surveys, <emph type="i">see</emph> A. Christians, <emph type="i">Tax Activist and the Global Movement for Development through Transparency</emph>, in <emph type="i">Tax, Law and Development </emph>(Y. Brauner &amp; M. Stewart eds., Edward Elgar 2013); Tax Justice Network ed., <emph type="i">The Greatest Invention: Tax and the Campaign for a Just Society</emph> (Commonwealth 2015). But these activist movements should be careful enough not to lose sight of how rich nation states and the global legal and political institutions they help create are ultimately “the ones to blame” for the lack of legitimacy and the unfairness of international tax. In a way, they should avoid promoting a strategy criticized by Chantal Mouffe for resulting in what she calls “withdrawal from” existing institutional structures, as opposed to “engagement with”. <emph type="i">See </emph>Mouffe, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_95">n. 95</xref>. This has not gone unnoticed in the tax scholarship. As Allison Christians stresses, the media and many individuals and organizations protesting against global tax injustices have focused too much on tax cheats and too little on the law. They have invoked morality and pushed for soft law mechanisms, conflating evasion and avoidance, instead of demanding legal and political change. <emph type="i">See</emph> A. Christians, <emph type="i">Avoidance, Evasion, and Taxpayer Morality</emph>, 44 Wash. U.J.L. &amp; Pol’y 39 (2014). </p>
               </footnote> Some developing countries, such as Bangladesh, China, India and Singapore, have already begun to question the way international tax norms have been drafted in the interests of developed countries.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_176" label="176.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>their respective Responses to the UN Subcommittee on BEPS Issues for Developing Countries, available at <url target="http://www.un.org/esa/ffd/tax/Beps/CommentsIndia_BEPS.pdf">http://www.un.org/esa/ffd/tax/Beps/CommentsIndia_BEPS.pdf</url>.</p>
               </footnote> The strategy, however, was badly received by Robert Stack, a US Treasury Deputy Assistant Secretary for International Tax Affairs, who “expressed a concern that countries such as India and China are seeking to use the OECD’s BEPS project to ‘recalibrate the global paradigm’ on source and residence-state taxation that has been in place since the 1920s’”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_177" label="177.">
                  <p> J. Fuller &amp; D. Forst, <emph type="i">The U.S. Position on BEPS</emph>, 24 Intl. Tax R. 59 (2013).</p>
               </footnote> Such recalibration is indeed what these countries should aim for. In publicly expressing their dissent with the BEPS initiative, such nations have become the harshest critics of the OECD’s tax work so far, coming from the “Global South”. Though not yet “global norm-makers”, they are visibly transforming themselves into active “global norm-shakers”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_178" label="178.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See</emph>, e.g., J. Li, <emph type="i"><extxref target="bit_2015_06_o2_6">China and BEPS: From Norm-Taker to Norm-Shaker</extxref></emph>, 69 Bull. Intl. Taxn. 6/7 (2015), Journals IBFD.</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>That is the way forward. Developing countries should target the pluralization of hegemonies in the postnational tax space through counterhegemonic projects and alternative epistemic communities.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_179" label="179.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>D. Kennedy, <emph type="i">Three Globalizations of Law and Legal Thought: 1850-2000</emph>, in<emph type="i"> The New Law and Economic Development: A Critical Appraisal</emph> p. 24 (D.M. Trubek &amp; A.Santos eds., Cambridge University 2006): “progressive elites of the periphery can and should devise national progressive strategies, rather than accept the prescription of the center”.</p>
               </footnote> Given that no political change is likely to come from developed countries, marginalized nations need to find other avenues for exercising resistance and demanding global change. For multilateralism to be more than mere wishful thinking, the aim must ultimately be for the creation of a multipolar world order, where power is more equally distributed between regional poles, and thus exerted in a more balanced manner.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_180" label="180.">
                  <p> As Mouffe argues, “[w]e hear a lot about the necessity of an effective ‘multilateralism’. But multilateralism in an unipolar world will always be an illusion. As long as a single hegemonic power exists, it will always be the one that decides if it will take into consideration the opinion of the other nations or act alone. A real multilateralism requires the existence of a plurality of centres of decision and some sort of equilibrium – even if it is only a relative one – among various power”. Mouffe, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_149">n. 149</xref>, at p. 116. <emph type="i">Accord</emph> Teixeira, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_95">n. 95</xref>, at pp. 271-292.</p>
               </footnote> For this reason, a political project that intends to bring about a legitimate world order in tax – or any other field, for that matter – should be modelled on a “<emph type="i">demoi</emph>-cracy”, an idea primarily developed for the EU context.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_181" label="181.">
                  <p> 
                     <emph type="i">See </emph>K. Nicolaïdis, <emph type="i">“We, the Peoples of Europe...”</emph>, 83 Foreign Aff. 97, p. 101 (2004): “The EU is neither a union of democracies nor a union as democracy; it is a union of states and of peoples – a ‘<emph type="i">demoicracy</emph>’<emph type="i"> – </emph>in the making”; S. Besson, <emph type="i">Deliberative </emph>Demoi<emph type="i">-cracy in the European Union: Towards the Deterritorialization of Democracy</emph>, in <emph type="i">Deliberative Democracy and its Discontents</emph> p. 206 (S. Besson &amp; J.L. Martí eds., Ashgate 2006): “The idea of <emph type="i">demoi</emph>-cracy has now become an inseparable part of recent proposals attempting to remedy the democratic deficit in the European Union. It emphasizes the deliberation among many European <emph type="i">demoi</emph> rather than either one European <emph type="i">demos </emph>or many national <emph type="i">demoi</emph>”.</p>
               </footnote> In a situation involving multistate governance, democratic principles require the possibility of deliberation among many <emph type="i">demoi</emph>.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_182" label="182.">
                  <p> For an application of a similar reasoning, <emph type="i">see </emph>J. Bohman, <emph type="i">Democracy across Borders: From Dêmos to Dêmoi</emph> (The MIT 2007); F. Cheneval, <emph type="i">The Government of the Peoples: On the Idea and Principles of Multilateral Democracy </emph>(Palgrave Macmillan 2011).</p>
               </footnote>
            </p>
            <p>The institutionalization of such a model at the global level requires the development of three dimensions, insofar as “global democracy should be conceived of as pluralistic, deterritorialised and deliberative, i.e. in a nutshell as deliberative <emph type="i">demoi</emph>-cracy”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_183" label="183.">
                  <p> S. Besson, <emph type="i">Institutionalizing Global Demoi-cracy</emph>, in <emph type="i">Legitimacy, Justice and Public International Law</emph> pp. 59-60 (L.H. Meyer ed., Cambridge University 2009).</p>
               </footnote> To be sure, the goal is to build a “multilayered, multi-actor, multi-stratified system”,<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_184" label="184.">
                  <p> A.V. Teixeira, <emph type="i">Direito Público Transnacional: Por uma Compreensão Sistêmica das Esferas Transnacionais de Regulação Jurídica</emph> [<emph type="i">Transnational Public Law: For a Systemic Interpretation of the Transnational Spheres of Legal Regulation</emph>], 19 Revista Novos Estudos Jurídicos 400, p. 424 (2014).</p>
               </footnote> but one that is “on the mode of a ‘demoi-cracy’ composed of a multiplicity of diverse <emph type="i">demoi</emph> providing different spaces for ‘the exercise of democracy’”.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_185" label="185.">
                  <p> Mouffe, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_95">n. 95</xref>.</p>
               </footnote> Conceiving the world as politically constituted by peoples requires respect for each country’s economic, social, cultural and historical background, at the same time conferring upon its members (directly or indirectly) both the autonomy to engage in democratic contestation and the power to shape the rules of the international (tax) game.</p>
            <p>In such a frame of mind, those concerned with justice and development in the world must focus on finding new paths and strategies that can bolster the capabilities, leverage and bargaining powers of weaker states, reducing the gap in resources that separates them from the developed world.<footnote anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_186" label="186.">
                  <p>
                     <emph type="i"> See </emph>L. van Apeldoorn, <emph type="i">BEPS, Tax Sovereignty and Global Justice</emph>, 21 Crit. Rev. Intl. Soc. &amp; Pol. Phil. 4, pp. 16-17 (2016), criticizing Dietsch and Rixen’s proposal for disregarding distributional patterns among countries, and concluding that “while the OECD’s ostensible concern with effective tax sovereignty is laudable, ... the structure of [BEPS] proposals insufficiently addresses the injustice of current inequality in effective tax sovereignty. [...] [T]he principle of economic allegiance on its own does not protect states in their quest for FDI from tax competition (‘real’ tax competition) that may undermine their capacity to engage in redistributive programmes. [...] The principle of economic allegiance (which allocates tax jurisdiction in accordance with the economic activity of MNCs) is non-responsive to the distribution of fiscal self-determination between countries. The countries where MNCs conduct economic activities are not necessarily the countries that have low fiscal self-determination. Accordingly the OECD’s dependence on the principle of economic allegiance is misguided. [...] [R]evised principles of tax justice, based on an internationalist conception of justice that is concerned with securing the effective sovereignty of independent polities, may need to prescribe the creation of globally redistributive institutions”; Dagan, <emph type="i">supra </emph><xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_53">n. 53</xref>, at p. 10: “cooperation alone is no guarantee of justice and ... certain transfer payments between rich and poor countries might be required to ensure this”; Stewart, <emph type="i">supra</emph> <xref target="wtj_2018_04_int_1_fn_118">n. 118</xref>, at p. 309: “If we are to take the idea of international redistribution seriously, we therefore need to unpack the very concept of the “country” (or state) that has at its core the ability to tax and redistribute”.</p>
               </footnote> Only by doing so will these countries be able to challenge the structures in place and demand mitigation of global disparities.</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="wtj_2018_04_int_1_s_5" label="5.">
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>Moving in the direction of a more legitimate world tax order requires a direct confrontation with the asymmetry of power between states, as well as the problematic powerful global actors including international institutions, private groups and experts. These actors have been, for many decades, shaping tax law and policy to the benefit of a few through technical discourses behind closed doors. Owing to these entrenched power structures, it is not clear that an ITO, even if nominally inclusive, could make a real contribution to improving the position of marginalized countries in international tax policymaking. </p>
         <p>Instead of trying to derive substantive principles of international taxation and enforcing them by a supranational institution, the initiative should start from the bottom up, critically evaluating the current practices of global tax governance, so as to find ways to make them more attuned with democratic principles. For a genuine multilateral democratic order to become a reality, it is imperative to continue pushing towards a multipolar and plural world that is open to the formation of several autonomous regional blocs, reversing the concentration of political power, thereby decentralizing and diffusing authority in the global arena.</p>
         <p>In the end, what would be desirable is the establishment of strong local and regional platforms for political articulation, resistance and contestation, where developing countries could truly engage with each other in a collaborative effort to advance their fiscal and economic interests. That way, they would be able to demand more profound reforms in the ITR, directed towards global equality and socioeconomic development. Through regional integration, South-South cooperation, and the like, these countries might be able to exercise their political voice, in order to promote a more progressive and pro-development tax agenda than the one driven by the OECD, providing support for alternative policies on how to deal, in a more equitable and fair way, with tax base erosion. </p>
         <p>This is certainly not an easy task. But it is a necessary first step for developing countries to be able to achieve their emancipatory and transformative goals. As long as they remain excluded from the processes of tax policymaking that take place on the global stage, they will never be able to shake up the status quo, which tilts the playing field decidedly in favour of countries in the “Global North” and perpetuates centuries-old inequalities and hierarchies.</p>
      </section>
   </chapbody>
</country-chap>